好的，有人听到我说话吗？
Alright, anyone hear me?
好的。
Good.
好的，今天我们要讲 meltdown ，
Alright today we got meltdown,
我读这篇论文是因为，
the reason why I'm reading this paper is that,
安全一直是一个话题，
security has kind of been a topic all along
在内核的设计中出现了很多问题，
and comes up a lot in the design of the kernels,
我们在课程中谈到的，
that we talked about in the class
我们所知的主要策略，我们已经讨论过，
and as we know the main strategy, we've talked about for,
内核主要提供安全的是隔离，
what it main for a kernel to provide security is isolation,
用户程序可以从内核读取数据，
in the sense that user programs can read data from the kernel
但是用户程序不能读取其他用户的数据，
and user programs can't read other user's data from other user programs,
我们看到的特别技术，
and the specific techniques that you know we've seen,
操作系统为了实现隔离，
operating systems used in order to get isolation
或者硬件中的用户管理者模式之类的东西，
or things like the user supervisor mode in the hardware
以及硬件中的页表，
and the page tables in the hardware
以及一些设计精良的内核软件，
as well as just sort of well designed kernel software,
比如系统调用是防御性的，
like the system calls are all defensive
对于如何使用用户提供的指针。
about how they use user supplied pointers.
但是值得思考的是，
But it's worth thinking about,
看看这类事情是如何出错的，
looking at examples of how this kind of stuff goes wrong,
我的意思是，内核努力提供隔离和安全，
I mean in fact, you know kernels try hard to provide isolation and security,
但是出现了一些问题。
but there are problems that come up.
这篇论文是最有趣的问题之一，
And this paper is a one of the most interesting problems,
这是最近出现的操作系统安全问题。
that's come up with operating system security in recent times.
Meltdown 出现了，
Meltdown is came out,
它在 2018 年初发布的，不久之前，
it was published at the beginning of 2018 so not too long ago,
很多人像我一样都觉得很惊讶，
and a lot of people like me found it surprising
而且非常令人不安，
and actually pretty disturbing,
非常令人不安地对于用户内核隔离。
pretty disturbing attack on user kernel isolation.
这破坏了信仰或者说某种非常基本的假设，
It really undermined faith or sort of this very basic assumption,
硬件提供的页表会让你隔离，
that the page tables that the hardware supplies just get you isolation
这就是故事的结束，
and that's the end of the story
而这次攻击完全不支持这种观点，
and this attack does not support that view at all,
此外，它是一个例子，
further it was an example of,
最近几个称为微架构攻击的例子之一，
one of a number of recent examples of what's called a microarchitectural attack,
涉及利用 CPU 内部隐藏的实现细节的攻击，
an attack that involves exploitation of hidden implementation details inside the CPU,
甚至不知道 CPU 是如何工作的，
that are often not even known how this how CPU's work,
但是人们猜测，
but people guess
而且他们基于正确猜测实现攻击，
and they're able to make successful attacks based on correct guesses
关于 CPU 实现隐藏细节（的猜测）。
about hidden details of CPU implementation.
Meltdown 是可以修复的，
Meltdown turns out to be fixable
而且似乎完全修复了，
and seems to be pretty completely fixed,
但尽管如此，这还是让人们感到恐惧，
but nevertheless people it sort of set people up to fear,
可能会有穷的类似的微架构攻击。
that there might be an open-ended supply of similar microarchitectural attacks.
所以这是最近发生的一件非常重要，值得我们了解的事情。
So it's a pretty important recent event worth understanding.
让我先从攻击的核心开始，
Let me start by just laying out the basic core of the attack,
我们会谈谈这里发生的事情，
and we'll talk about what's going on here,
但这是代码的简化版本，
but this is somewhat simplified version of the code
论文中关于攻击如何运作的，
in the paper for how the attack works,
基本想法是你是一个攻击者，
the basic idea is that you're an attacker,
出于某种原因，你可以在某些计算机上运行软件，
and for one reason or another you're able to run software on some computer,
有一些你想偷的秘密，
that has some secrets that you'd like to steal,
你不能直接获得秘密，
you're not allowed to directly get up the secrets,
但它们在内存中，可能是内核内存或其他进程内存，
but they're in memory, maybe kernel memory or another processes memory,
但是你已经能够运行一个进程，
but you've been able to run a process,
可能是因为你登录了 Athena 那样的分时机，
maybe because you logged into a time sharing machine like Athena machine,
或者是因为你在一些托管服务上购买了时间。
or maybe because you bought time on some hosting service.
所以，攻击允许你运行一个程序，
So what the attack allows you to do is run a program
你在自己的内存中声明一个缓冲区，
in which you declare a buffer in your own memory,
所以这个 buf 是一个普通的用户可以访问的内存，
so this buf is a just ordinary user memory that's accessible,
你有想窃取的东西的内核的虚拟地址。
you have the virtual address in the kernel of something that you're interested in stealing.
你说，
And you issue,
我在这里写的是
what I'm writing out here is sort of
C 和汇编语言的混合体，
you know mix of C and assembler,
但我在第 3 行的意思是，
but what I mean in line 3 is that,
你有要窃取的数据的内核虚拟地址，
you have the address of the kernel virtual address of the data
你想窃取的地址在 r1 中，
you want to steal at register one or r1
在第 3 行，这是间接引用 r1 的指令，或者仅仅假设这是取消引用寄存器1并将其结果加载到寄存器2中的指令，
and line 3 were, or just imagine that this is instructions to dereference register one
并将它的结果放入 r2 中，
and load its results into register two,
这就是我们要运行的指令，
that's the instruction that we're going to run,
然后有一条指令，
and then there's an instruction that,
获取 r2 的低位，
just gets the low bit of register two,
所以这个攻击，这个特定版本的攻击只读取了一个位，
so this attack, this particular version of this attack reads just a single bit,
只有内核的一个内存位置的一个低位，
just one low bit of a one memory location from the kernel,
用它乘以 4096 ，
multiply that four thousand 4096
因为它要么是 0 ，要么是 1 ，
and since it's either zero or one,
这意味着 r2 最终是 0 或 4096 ，
that means that r2 will end up being zero or 4096
然后我们简单地读取 buf 的内容，
and then we simply read the contents of our buf,
这是一个用户内存缓冲，
which is a buffer of user memory,
我们简单地读取缓冲器 0 或缓冲器 4096 ，
we simply read either buffer 0 or buffer 4096,
这就是基本的攻击。
and that's the basic attack.
所以，有一个问题是，
So, one question is,
为什么这不能直接起作用，
why doesn't this just directly work,
第三行读取这个内核地址，
line 3 reading this kernel address,
我们能不能只从内核读取地址。
can we just read addresses from the kernel.
不，我们都相信答案不可能是肯定的，
No, no, we all have faith that the answer can't possibly be yes,
我们不可能在用户空间直接从内核中读取，
we can't possibly be able to just directly read from the kernel for in user space,
CPU 的机制，有时这个不能工作，
and the machinery that we know the CPU somehow is invoking to make this not work out,
当我们使用内核虚拟地址时，
is that when we use kernel virtual address,
这意味着在页表中查找，
that implies a lookup in the page table,
在页表中有权限位，
and there's permission bits in the page table
并且我们假设操作系统
and we're just assuming that the operating system
没有对内核虚拟地址的页表条目设置标志，
has not set the flag in the page table entries for kernel virtual addresses,
没有设置允许用户使用这些地址的标志，
has not set that flag that allows users to use those addresses,
那是 RISC-V 上的 PTE_U 标志，
that's the PTE_U flag on the RISC-V
所以，这个指令必须失败，一定会导致页面错误。
and that therefore this instruction must fail, must cause a page fault.
事实上，如果我们运行这段代码，
And indeed, if we ran this code,
这条指令会导致页面错误，
this instruction would cause a page fault,
如果我们在这之后加一个代码，
and if we tried to, if we added a code after this,
比如打印寄存器 3 中的值，
to say print the value in register 3,
我们在第 3 行得到一个页面错误，
we get a page fault on line three,
我们永远不会得到 print 语句，
and we never get to the print statement,
我们发现不能直接从内核窃取数据。
and we find we couldn't directly steal data out of the kernel.
然而，正如论文所示的那样，这个序列被证明是有用的。
Nevertheless, the sequence turned out to be useful as the paper shows.
这篇论文假设的一件事，
One thing that, one thing that the paper assumes
在很大程度上不再是真的，
which is no longer really true for the most part is that,
内核映射到每个用户进程地址空间，
the kernel is mapped into every user processes address space,
在页表中，用户代码运行全套内核 PTE ，
that is user user codes running a full set of kernel PTE is present in the page table,
但它们把 PTE_U 清除了，
but they have the PTE_U bit clear,
所以，用户代码会得到错误，
so user code will get a fault,
如果它试图使用内核虚拟地址，
if it tries to use a kernel virtual address,
所以所有这些映射，
so all those mappings in,
在写这篇论文的时候，
at the time this paper was written,
所有这些映射都在那里，当在用户空间执行时，
all those mappings were there, when executing in user space,
它们只是不能被用户代码使用，
they just couldn't be used by user code
或者被用户代码使用时导致错误，
or they cause a fault, they were used by user code,
操作系统设计人员
and the reason why people by operating system designers
在运行用户代码时，同时映射内核和用户地址的原因是，
mapped both kernel and user addresses when running user code is
这使得系统调用速度相当快，
that made system calls quite a bit faster,
因为这意味着在发生系统调用时，
because that meant that on a system call happened,
你不必切换页表，
you don't have to switch page tables,
切换页表本身就需要时间，
and switching page tables just usually takes time itself
并且通常还会导致 CPU 缓存刷新，
and also typically causes CPU caches to be flushed,
使得后续代码变慢。
which makes subsequent codes slower.
所以，人们得到了速度提升，
So people got a boost,
通过始终在用户空间中映射用户和内核映射。
by mapping both user and kernel mappings always in user space.
但这个攻击正依赖于这种习惯。
But this attack actually, and this attack relies on that habit.
好的，我来解释一下这里发生了什么，
Okay, I'm going to explain what's going on here,
使得这段代码有用，
that makes this code useful,
但是在我开始之前，
but before I do that,
关于这个代码片段，有没有什么问题？
any any questions about, any questions about this, this code fragment?
我想知道你是否可以重复，
I was actually wondering if you could repeat,
你刚才所说的内核到用户的映射，
what you just said about kernel to user mapping,
并且不需要寄存器。
and don't [really] register.
好的，我们看一下，
Okay, let's see,
你知道在 xv6 中，
you know how in xv6,
当进程在用户空间中执行时，
when you're executing when the process is executing in user space,
如果你查看页表，
if you look at the page table,
页表有用户地址映射，
that page table has mapping for the user addresses,
比如 trampoline 页面，
and for like the trampoline page
trampoline 页面，没有其他的了，
and the trapframe page and nothing else,
这就是 xv6 的工作。
so that's how xv6 works.
这篇论文假设的页表跟那个不同，
The page table that this paper assumes where different from that,
在写这篇论文的时候，
this, in the time this paper was written,
大多数操作系统都有，
most operating systems would have
在页表中有一套完整的内核映射，
a set complete set of kernel mappings in the page table,
当用户代码运行时，
while user code was running,
所以，所有那些页表条目都会在那里，
and so all those page table entries would be there,
当用户代码运行时，所有内核页表条目都会在那里，
all the kernel page table entries would be there when user code is running,
但是由于每一个那些页表条目中的 PTE_U 位被清除，
but since the PTE_U bit was clear on each of those page table entries,
用户代码不能使用内核虚拟地址，
user code wouldn't actually be able to use a kernel virtual address,
但是映射就在那里，
but the mappings were there,
原因是，当你进行系统调用时，
and the reason for that is that when you do a system call,
你不必切换页表，
you didn't have to switch page tables,
因为进行系统调用进入内核，
because you do a system call into the kernel
当你使用相同的页表时，
and boom you're using the same page table,
现在你可以使用所有这些内核 PTE ，
but now you can use all those kernel PTEs,
因为你处于管理者模式，
because you're in supervisor mode,
这节省了很多时间，
and that saved a bunch of time
在系统调用时进出内核。
getting into and out of the kernel during system calls.
每个人都用这个技巧，
Everybody, everybody used that technique,
这几乎可以肯定是英特尔的想法，
and that was almost certainly what Intel had in mind,
关于你应该如何编写操作系统。
for how you should write an operating system.
好的，所以在整篇论文中，
Okay, so that for the whole paper,
假设攻击的结构是这样的，
that structure is assumed for the attack,
当然避免它，
of course getting rid of it
是解决这个问题最直接的办法，
is what's the most immediate solution to this problem,
但是，在编写这篇论文时，
but the time, the paper was written
所有内核映射都存在于用户空间中。
all those kernel mappings were present in user space.
还有其他问题吗？
Other questions?
所以你需要知道你想得到的地址。
So you need to know the address and you want to get.
是的，没错，就是这样。
Yeah, that's right, it is and.
这是一个很好的观点，
So you know that's a good point,
你需要知道内核虚拟地址，
you need to know the kernel virtual address
这可能不是开玩笑的。
and that's actually maybe no joke.
你可能认为这会让攻击变得更难。
Yeah, you might think that would make the attack harder.
但是首先从安全的哲学观点来看，
But first of all point of philosophy in security,
你需要假设攻击者有无限的时间和耐心。
you just have to assume that the attacker has infinite time and patience.
如果在一些有价值的秘密，
And if there are some valuable secrets,
他们可能愿意花几个月的时间试图窃取这个秘密，
they are probably willing to spend a couple of months trying to steal that secret,
或者更长时间，
or longer, right,
因为这可能是某人的密码，
because you know it's gonna be somebody's password,
它保护各种有价值的东西，
that protects all kinds of valuable stuff,
可能是钱或秘密电子邮件。
maybe money or secret email.
所以，这意味着攻击者可能有时间
So that means for example the attacker probably has time
尝试每一个内核地址，
to try every single kernel address, right,
在那里寻找任何珍贵的数据，
looking for whatever precious data there after,
可能是密码，
maybe a password,
或者攻击者可能有时间学习查看内核代码，
or the attacker may have time to study to look through the kernel code
查看典型的编译内核并查找地址，
and look through typical compiled kernels and find addresses
可以在他们的内核中放打印语句，
and maybe put print statements in their kernel
检查内核内存中的数据结构，
to examine the structure of data in kernel memory,
直到他们了解内核是如何工作的，
until they understand how the kernel works,
才能在这里找到这里的地址。
well enough to be able to get an address here.
因为这个游戏一直在进行，
Now, actually, because this game has been going on,
这个游戏的其他版本，
other versions of this game,
安全游戏已经进行了很长一段时间了，
the security game had been going out for a long time,
内核会防御这些攻击，
kernels actually defend themselves against attacks
涉及猜测内核地址的攻击，
that involve guessing kernel addresses,
这篇论文实际上提到的一件事是，
and one of the things that was actually mentioned this paper is
这称为内核地址空间布局随机化，
this called thing called kernel address space layout randomization,
所以现代内核加载内核到随机地址，
so modern kernels actually load the kernel at a random address,
为了使猜测内核虚拟地址变得更加困难，
in order to make it harder to guess kernel virtual addresses,
早在这篇论文发表之前，他们就这样做了，
and they did this before this, long before this paper came out,
因为它有助于防止其他攻击。
because it was helpful in defeating other attacks.
所以，这就是游戏，
So, so this is the game,
但是我们必须假设攻击者，
but we have to assume that the attacker,
最终，攻击者可能会赢得这个游戏。
in the end, the attacker will probably win this game.
好吧，我们假设攻击者知道一个内核虚拟地址，
Okay, so let's just assume the attacker either knows a [] kernel virtual address to look at
或者猜到一个，或者愿意穷尽每一个地址。
or can guess one or is willing to exhaustively try every address.
这篇论文认为这是一个看似合理的策略，
And the paper suggests that that's a plausible strategy,
一旦有了 meltdown 。
once you have meltdown.
好的。
Okay.
好的，接下来会发生什么，
Okay, so what's gonna happen,
所以我们想知道这段代码怎么会，
well, so we're wondering how can this code be,
可能被攻击者利用，
possibly be useful to an attacker,
答案是，
and the answer has to do,
如果 CPU 的工作方式和你在 CPU 手册上看到的一样，
like if the way CPU's work was just what you read in the CPU manual,
这个攻击当然是没有意义的，
this attack clearly is nonsense,
比如它会在指令 3 失败，
like it'll fault at instruction 3
并且结束，
and that'll be the end of it,
但事实证明， CPU 的工作方式比手册中的复杂得多，
but it turns out CPU's work in far more complex ways than is in the manual,
这个攻击方式成功的原因是，
and the way the reason the attack works is
因为一些 CPU 的实现细节。
because of some CPU implementation details.
实际上，攻击依赖于两个主要的东西，
And there's actually two main things that the attack relies on,
一种是 CPU 称为预测执行的实现技巧，
one is implementation trick of CPU's called speculative execution,
我将首先谈到这一点，
which I'll talk about first,
另一个攻击所依赖的实现技巧是 CPU 进行缓存的方式。
and the other implementation trick the attack relies on is the way CPU's do caching.
好的。
Okay.
所以首先是预测执行，
So first speculative execution,
我也有一个代码示例，
let me, I have a code example for that also,
现在我说的不是安全问题，
and for the moment I'm not talking about security at all,
预测执行只是一种提高 CPU 性能的技术，
the speculative execution this stuff is just a technique to improve the performance of CPUs,
一种 CPU 使用的优化技巧，
some optimization trick that CPUs use,
想象一下，我们正在运行这段代码，
so imagine that we're just, we have, which is running this code,
这是一个有点人为的例子，
this is somewhat contrived example,
但在某种程度上说明了预测执行的意义，
but it's sort of illustrates what speculative execution is all about,
假设我在寄存器 0 中有个地址，
supposing I have address in some say register zero,
因为我程序的逻辑，
and just because the logic my program,
地址要么有效要么无效，
the address is either valid or not valid,
在某些情况下，它可能包含 0 ，
maybe it contains zero if under some circumstances,
比如我们还没有初始化我的数据。
like we haven't initialize my data yet.
所以这假设在内存中的某个地方有一个 valid 变量，
So this will assume there's a valid variable that's sitting in memory somewhere,
所以在使用这个地址之前，
so before using the address here,
在第 4 行中的寄存器 0 中的地址，
so this address in register zero here on line 4,
我们要测试，
we're going to test,
我们要从内存中加载 valid ，
we're gonna load valid from memory,
如果 valid 为 1 ，我们将使用这个地址，
and we're only going to use the address if valid is set to 1,
如果 valid 为 0 ，我们将看不到地址，
then if valid is set to 0, we are not going to see address at all,
如果 valid 为 1 ，那么我们将间接引用这个地址，
and if valid is set to one, then we're going to dereference the address,
把它指向的数据加载到寄存器 2 ，
you know load the data it points to at register 2,
然后加一，这没什么关系，
and add one to it and it doesn't really matter,
我们要用加载的数据做点什么，
we're going to do something with that data we loaded,
在这种情况下，对它加 1 ，
in this case, add one to it
并将寄存器 3 设置为那个数据加 1 。
and set register 3 equal to the data plus one.
好的，在一个简单的 CPU 实现中，
Alright, well, in a simple CPU implementation,
在第 2 行中，你可以加载，
at line 2 here, you can load,
valid 是一个位于内存中的变量，
the valid is a variable sitting in memory in RAM,
你必须发布一些，
and you have to issue some kind of,
这个会，
this is going to be,
第 2 行会使用 load 指令从内存中读取 valid ，
line 2 is going to be some sort of load instruction that reads valid out of RAM,
或者相等，如果我们必须从内存中加载它，
or else being equal if we actually have to load it from RAM,
那需要数百次循环，在我们的 2GHz 机器上，
that'll take hundreds of cycles on our say two GHz machine,
任何从内存加载需要数百次循环，
like any load that actually has to go to RAM will take hundreds of cycles,
机器可以执行一条指令，
the machine can execute an instruction,
每个周期最多执行一条指令，
up to an instruction every cycle,
所以如果我们要在这里等待几百个周期，
so if we actually had to wait a couple of hundred cycles here,
机器会在这里闲置数百个周期，
we'd be the machine to be sitting there idling for hundreds hundreds of cycles,
浪费时间。
sort of wasting its time.
因为这是一个显著的减速，
And because that's a significant significant slowdown, right,
如果一切顺利，
if everything went well,
我们能够在每个周期执行一条指令，
we'd be able to execute an instruction every cycle,
而不是每几百个周期执行一次。
instead of every couple hundred cycles.
所有现代的 CPU 都使用一种叫做分支预测的东西，
All modern, all serious modern CPUs do use something called branch prediction,
这个 if 语句是一个分支，
so this if statement is a branch,
如果我们把它变成机器指令，
if we actually turned it into machine instructions,
我们看到这里是一个分支，
we see there was a branch here,
这是一个条件分支，
and it's a conditional branch,
分支基于这个寄存器 1 是否等于 1 的测试，
branch based on this test whether register 1 is equal to 1,
而 CPU 所做的是，
and what CPUs do is,
它们使用叫做分支预测的东西，
they use what's called branch branch prediction,
也就是说，对于每个分支，
that is for every branch,
CPU 都会记住信息的缓存，
more or less the CPU essentially remembers a cache of information
关于程序中的每个分支，
about each of the branches in your program,
或者至少每个最近执行的分支，
or at least each recently executed branch,
然后记起，那个分支是[拿了]还是没拿，
then remembers oh did that branch was the branch taken or not taken,
如果 CPU 没有足够的信息来预测，
and if the CPU doesn't have enough information to predict,
这基于你上次执行分支的预测，
so that's prediction based on the last time you executed the branch,
即使 CPU 没有预测，
even if the CPU doesn't have a prediction,
它仍然可以继续执行指令，
it may still just go ahead and execute the instructions,
无论是你去的分支，
either that the branch takes you to
或没有去的指令，假设分支没有选择，
or the fail to instructions, assuming the branch wasn't taken,
甚至在 CPU 知道条件是否为真之前，
that is, even before the CPU knows whether this conditional is true,
它会选择一种或另一种方式，并开始沿着这条路径执行，
it'll choose one way or the other and start executing down that path,
尽管这可能是条错误的路径，还不知道。
even though it might be the wrong path, doesn't know yet.
所以在这种情况下，
And so in this case,
也许在这个加载完成之前，
maybe before this load completes,
在知道 valid 的值之前，
and before the value of valid is known,
CPU 已经开始执行指令 4 ，
the CPU may start executing instruction 4
并加载 r0 中的值，
and do the load with whatever value is sitting in r0,
它可能是也可能不是有效的指针，
which may or may not be a valid pointer
一旦加载产生了一些结果，
and once that load yields something,
甚至可以加 1 ，
maybe even add one to it
并将寄存器 3 设置为那个值。
and set register 3 equal to that value.
也许在很久之后，
And then maybe a long time later,
当第 2 行的加载最终完成时，
when this load at line 2 finally completes,
现在我们知道 valid 的值是什么，
now we know what the value of valid is,
CPU 会，这个真的，
the CPU will then, this real,
它跟踪了这样一个事实，
you know you know it kept track of the fact,
它执行第 4 行和第 5 行，
that it executed lines 4 and 5
但并不知道这样做是否合适，
without really knowing whether that was proper,
如果 valid 是 1 ，那没问题，继续运行，
if valid is 1, then that's fine, it just keeps going,
如果 valid 为 0 ， CPU 足够聪明
if valid is 0, then the CPU has enough cleverness
来取消它执行第 4 行和第 5 行的结果，
to cancel the effects of its execution of line 4 and 5,
并在第 7 行的分支之后的适当位置重新开始执行。
and restart execution in the proper place after the branch at line 7.
这种在你知道之前执行代码，
And this execution of code before you know
你是否应该执行代码之前，被称为推测，
whether you really should be executing it is called speculation,
再说一次，重点是性能，
and again, the point is performance,
如果 CPU 猜测是正确的，
if the CPU guess is right,
那么它在开始执行这些指令时就有了很大的优势，
then it got a big head start executing these instructions,
而不必等待昂贵的内存加载。
and didn't have to wait for the expensive memory load.
对于这意味着什么，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about what this means?
好的，这个机器，硬件， CPU 里的晶体管都是非常复杂的，
Okay, this machinery, the hardware, the transistors in the CPU for speculation are extremely complex,
在 CPU 中有大量的工作来完成这项工作，
there's a huge amount going on in the CPU to make this work,
没有一个是公开的，
none of which is published, right,
整个都是英特尔内部的东西，
it's a whole Intel internal stuff,
不在机器手册里。
not in, not in the machine manual.
所以围绕 meltdown 和攻击，
So surrounding meltdown and attacks
是一个很大的猜测，
like it is a huge amount of speculation
关于 CPU 内部可能发生的事，
about what's probably going on inside the CPU
使这种攻击工作或不工作。
in order to make such attack work or not work.
好了，还是回到预测。
Okay, back to speculation though.
有一件事是，
One thing that's going on is that,
为了取消推测预测失败的执行，
in order to undo speculative failed speculative mispredicted speculative execution,
机器保留了寄存器的影子版本，
the machine had keeps shadow versions of registers essentially,
它被分配给寄存器 2 ，寄存器 3 ，
you know it assigned to registers 2, register 3,
它分配一个临时的寄存器，
but it's assigning kind of a temporary registers,
如果预测成功，
if speculation succeeds,
那些影子寄存器会变为真实寄存器，
then those registers those shadow registers become the real registers,
如果失败，
if it fails,
CPU 会丢弃那些影子寄存器。
then those shadow registers discarded the CPU discards the shadow registers.
所以这两个任务 r2 和 r3 就像从来没有发生过。
So these two assignments r2 and r3 would just be as if they never happened.
所以，在这段代码中，
So in this code,
我们需要考虑如果寄存器 0 是有效指针会发生什么，
we need to think about what happens if register 0 is a valid pointer
还有如果它不是一个有效的指针呢？
and what happens if it's not a valid pointer, right.
如果我们预测执行第 4 行，
If we're speculatively executing line 4,
并且寄存器 2 是有效指针，
and register 2 is a valid pointer,
然后 CPU 会执行加载，
then it turns out the CPU will actually do the load,
至少加载到寄存器 2 的临时版本中，
and loaded into at least the transient version of register 2,
所以我们会出去，
so we'll actually go out
尝试获取 r0 所指向的内容，
and and try to fetch what r0 points to
那么这肯定会工作，
and that will certainly work
如果 r0 指向的数据在缓存中，
if the data r0 is pointed to is sitting in the cache,
我不知道 CPU 是否会加载，
and I don't know if if the CPU will do the load,
如果它在缓存中未命中，
if it misses in the cache
它可能必须从内存中加载。
and has to load from RAM, it might.
但是，也许对我们来说更有趣的问题是，
But, maybe the more interesting question for us,
对于这个攻击，如果寄存器 0 不是有效的指针，
for this attack is what happens if register 0 is not a valid pointer,
在这种情况下，如果我们在这里预测执行，
in that case, if we're speculatively executing here,
机器在这里不会出错，
the machine can't fault at this point,
因为我们预测执行，
because we're speculatively executing,
机器不知道，它可以知道 r0 是无效的，
machine doesn't know, it may know that r0 was an invalid,
这个预测执行指令试图使用无效指针，无效地址，
that this speculatively executed instruction tried to use an invalid pointer, an invalid address,
但它不会产生页面错误，
but it can't page fault,
因为它不能这个执行
because it's not sure whether this execution
valid 是正确预测执行还是错误预测，
is valid is correct speculative execution or misspeculation,
所以它只是，
and so it's only,
所以，它不会在第 4 行产生错误，
so, so it can't actually raise a fault on line 4
直到 valid 的值是知道的，
until after valid value of valid is known,
在这个预测分支之后，
and after this branch, this speculative predicted branch,
在机器知道情况之后，
after we know after the machine knows what the condition is,
如果机器看到第 4 寄存器 0 是有效地址，
if the machine see if the machine's that line 4 sees oh register 0 is an valid address,
然后 valid 是 1 ，
and then valid turns out to be 1,
然后，只有这样，机器才会真正产生页面错误，
then, and only then does the machine actually generate the page fault,
如果 r0 是无效地址，则有效地址是 0 ，
if r0 is an invalid address, then valid turns out to be 0,
机器不会产生页面错误。
the machine does not generate a page fault.
所以，关于是否出错的决定
So the, the decision about whether to fault
可能会推迟数百个周期，
is deferred possibly for hundreds of cycles
直到 valid 的值是知道的，
until the value of valid is known,
这里的专业术语，
then the technical term for the point at which
指令是否被正确预测执行，
we know whether an instruction was correctly speculatively executed
而不是被丢弃，叫做 retirement 。
rather than being thrown away is called retirement.
所以我们说一条指令是预测的，
So we say an instruction is speculative
在某个时刻退出了，
and at some point it's retired,
那么我们知道它要么会被扔掉，
and that's when we know it's either going to be thrown away
要么是真实的，并应该提交到机器的可见状态，
or what's real and should be its effect should be committed to the visible state of the machine
这个规则是，
and the rule is that,
指令能退出，
instruction can only be retired,
如果首先完成了内存加载的执行，比如加 1 操作，
if first of all is finished executing loading memory, you're adding one to something,
以及它之前的每条指令，
and every instruction before it,
在它还没有退出之前就执行了，
was executed before it has also retired,
所以，第 4 行不能退出，
so this line 4 can't be retired
直到 valid 的加载完成，状态是可评估的，
until the load of valid completes and the conditions is evaluated,
只有这样才能退出，
only then can be retired,
所以它可能会出错，
so it's going to fault, it may it's gonna fault,
可能在内存加载后数百条指令之后，
possibly hundreds of instructions after it is the memory load,
或者想要加载内存。
or attempted to do the memory load.
作为这个攻击的关键细节，
And as a critical detail for this attack,
还有更多的。
there's an even more.
如果让它，
If lets its,
如果 r0 中的地址是无效的，
if the address in r0 is invalid
并且在页表中根本没有映射，
and has no mapping in the page table at all,
然后不知道会发生什么。
then actually don't know what happens.
如果 r0 中的地址具有页表映射，
If the address in r0 has a page table mapping,
但是没有权限，
but there's no permission for it,
也就是 PTE_U 标志没有设置，
that is the PTE_U flag is not set,
那么英特尔机器做的是，
then what Intel machines actually do is,
加载数据并将其分配到临时寄存器 2 中，
load that data and assign it into the transient register 2,
它可以被第 5 行的预测执行使用，
and where it can be used by the speculative execution of line 5,
所以即使 r0 是一个我们没有权限的地址，
so even if r0 was was an address for which we don't have permission,
因为它是内核地址，
because it's a kernel address,
我们仍然会看到它的值加载到 r3 中，它的值加 1 ，
we'll still see it's value loaded into r3 and its value plus 1,
抱歉，我们看不到它，但它会加载到 r2 中，
sorry, we won't see it, but it will be loaded into r2
再加上 1 到 r3 ，
and that plus one at r3
然后当这个加载退出后，
and then when this load is retired,
机器会意识到那是一个无效的加载，
the machine will realize aha, that was an invalid load,
因为页表条目不允许它，
because the page table entry didn't allow it,
所以我们会生成一个错误，
and so we're going to raise a fault,
并取消后续指令的执行，
and cancel the execution of the subsequent instructions,
并取消这个指令的结果，
and cancel the effects of this instruction,
回退对 r2 和 r3 的修改。
undo the modification to r2 and r3.
所以在这个例子中，有两种预测在进行，
So in this example, there's two speculations going on,
一个是我们在预测这个分支，
one is we're speculating about where this branch,
机器预测这个分支的去向，
machines speculating about where this branch went
只是说，不管它去哪条路，
and just saying oh it went one way or the other,
我只是想试试看，
just gonna give that a shot speculatively,
另外，每次加载后都会有预测执行，
in addition there's speculative execution after each load,
我们预测，
we're essentially speculating about
机器预测那个加载是否成功，关于加载是否成功完成。
whether the machine is speculating about whether that load complete successfully.
在加载的情况下，英特尔机器总是继续运行，
And in the case of a load, Intel machines always just go on,
如果可以提供数据，
you know if data could be provided,
因为它在缓存中，
because it's in the cache,
或者至少页表条目存在，权限不存在，
and at least the page table entry exists, permissions are not,
机器将预测继续执行，
the machine will speculatively continue to execute
只有在退出时，
and only on retirement,
加载才会产生故障，
the load will actually generate the fault,
这将导致预测被取消。
and that will cause the speculation to be cancelled.
好的，关于这个东西，有什么问题吗？
Alright, any questions about this stuff?
我有点困惑第二种猜测，
I'm a little confused about, the second speculation
它将 r0 加载到 r2 中，
which is loading r0 into r2,
那么，这是否意味着将 r0 的值加载到 r2 中，
so, does that mean that like the value of r0 is loaded into r2
并在稍后检查标志？
and the flags are checked later?
是的，发生了什么，是的，完全正确，
Yes, yes, so what happens, yes, that's exactly, right,
所以实际发生的情况是，
so what actually happens is that
在预测阶段，
during the speculative phase,
不管 r0 指向的是什么，
whatever it is that r0 points to,
如果它指向什么东西，
if there's sort of if it points to anything,
如果 r0 指向任何东西，
if r0 points to anything,
那么内存位置的数据将被加载到 r2 中，
then the data that memory location will be loaded into r2,
稍后，当这个加载退出时，
later, when this load is retired,
然后会检查权限，
and it turned, then the permissions will be checked,
如果我们没有加载的权限，
and if we didn't have permission to do that load,
那么所有后续指令结果会被取消，
then all subsequent instructions effects will be cancelled,
所有这些寄存器的修改都会被撤销，
like all these modifications registere will be undone,
错误会出现，
and fault will be raised,
就像指令 4 之前的机器核寄存器一样。
with the state of the machines and registers as they were just before instruction 4.
好的，这很有趣。
Okay, that's interesting.
是的。
Yes.
是的，我还有一个问题，
Yes, I also have a question,
是否有限制 CPU 的方法，
is there no possible way to restrict the CPU
在预测加载之前限制 CPU 检查权限。
from checking permissions before doing a speculative load.
你的意思是，有没有办法让机器在加载之前做检查？
You mean, is there a way to cause the machine to do the check before the load?
是的，我想更具体一点，
Yes, I guess more concrete,
这是这个问题的唯一原因，
like the only reason this is a problem or,
但是其中一种方法是我们只加载一个页面，
but one of the ways is that we're just loading a page that,
如果我们意识到它的权限会变坏，
if we can be aware that it has permissions that are going to be bad somehow,
我们访问一个我们不应该能够访问的页面，
we're accessing a page that we don't we shouldn't be able to access,
预测执行能否取消，
the can the speculative execution be cancelled,
假设我们可以读取这些权限。
given that we can read these permissions.
是的，就是，
Yes, in a, yes that's,
好的，有两个答案，
yeah, well, there's two answers,
一个是，这不是英特尔 CPU 的实际工作方式，
one is that's not the way the Intel chips CPUs actually worked,
另一个答案是是的，
and the other answer is yes, it would have been,
我相信，那会更简单，
I I believe it would have been easy for them
对预测加载做强制检查，
to have done and enforce that check even for speculative loads,
即使在预测寄存器 2 中，也永远不会被写入。
so that even in speculation register 2 would never have been written.
所以，也许。
So maybe.
事实上，
And indeed, it turns out that,
我注意到论文中提到，
you may know, I've noticed the paper mentioned that,
meltdown 似乎不适用于 AMD CPU ，
the meltdown seems not to work on AMD CPUs,
即使 AMD CPU 的使用手册与 Intel CPU 相同，
even though AMD CPUs, the instruction manual is the same as for Intel CPUs,
是相同的指令集，也就是相同的东西，
essentially on the same instruction set and the instructions mean the same things,
这个攻击在 AMD CPU 上不起作用，
the attack doesn't work on AMD CPUs
人们普遍认为原因是 AMD CPU ，
and it's widely believed that the reason is that AMD CPUs,
即使是预测执行时，
even when speculatively executing,
if you don't have permission to read this address,
甚至不会预测加载值到 r2 中，
won't even speculatively loads the value to r2,
这就是为什么攻击在 AMD CPU 上不起作用的原因，
and that's why the attack didn't work on AMD CPUs
最近的英特尔 CPU 显然已经采用了这种方法，
and recent Intel CPUs apparently have adopted that approach,
不会预测加载，如果它们没有权限。
and actually won't won't speculatively load, if they don't have permissions.
据我所知，
And as far as I know,
这里没有明显的性能损失，
there's no particular sacrifice at performance,
我想信息都在那里了，
I think the information was all there,
但我不知道，可能只是几个[]，
but for just I don't know, just say maybe a few [],
他们决定只在退出时使用。
they decided only to apply it on retirement.
因为他们似乎就是这样。
Because they seem to.
那非常有趣。
That's very interesting.
是的，我的意思是，我提醒你这里有很多猜测，
Yeah, I mean, let me just warn you this there's a lot of guesswork here,
我相信我说的是真的，
and I believe what I'm saying is true,
但是英特尔和 AMD 并没有披露发生的事情。
but in Intel and AMD have not been very revealing about what's going on.
好的，这里有一些很重要的术语，
Okay, thers's some terminology here that's important,
当你在 CPU 手册中读到，
the when you read in the manual for the CPU,
它说，加法指令使用两个寄存器，
that says oh you know an add instruction takes two registers
对它们相加，然后放到第三个寄存器中，
and adds them and puts them in a third,
这种设计方面的东西叫做架构，
that stuff, that aspect of the design is called architectural,
一种[]行为，
sort of [] behavior,
机器的[]行为，
the [] behavior of the machine,
所以，机器的[]行为是，
and so the [] behavior of machine is that,
如果你从某个地址加载时，产生页面错误，
if your load from an address you know permissions for you get a page fault [],
则不允许加载，
you're not allowed to load,
这与机器实际所做的不同，
that's in distinction to what the machines actually doing,
就是所谓的微体系结构。
which is called Micro-Architectural.
这是机器有预测执行，
That is actually the machine has speculating executions
做这些疯狂的事情，没有告诉你的，
doing all these crazy things without telling you,
CPU 设计者的目的，
and the intent of the CPU designers,
在设计所有这些复杂的微体系架构优化时，
when they design all these complex micro-architectural optimizations
它们是透明的，
is that they be transparent,
是的，它在内部做所有这些事情，
that yeah, it's doing all this stuff internally,
但是看起来你从程序中得到的结果
but it looks the results you get from programs
和一台更简单的机器上得到的结果是一样的，
are the same results you get from a simpler machine,
做了手册中简单的事情。
that just did the straightforward thing that was in the manual.
它们应该是透明的。
They are intended to be transparent
所以，比如，在某种程度上，
and so you know, for example, at some level,
Intel 在这里做的事情是透明的，
what Intel is doing here is transparent,
是的，也许在你加载内存的时候，他们没有检查权限，
yeah, maybe they don't check for permissions when you when you do the memory load,
但是如果退出有问题的话，
but if there was a problem on retirement,
它会取消所有这些影响，
it's gonna undo all these effects
所以你永远不会看到那些内存，
and so you'll never see that memory,
你不应该看到，
you weren't supposed to see,
所以，看起来和手册上说的一样，
so gosh that looks just like what the manual said,
你不允许加载没有权限的东西。
you're not allowed to load stuff you don't have permission for.
所以这个区别是，
So this distinction is,
这个攻击的很多内容，
a lot of what this attack is playing,
在这里，它知道所有攻击的东西，
on that it knows all the attack,
知道很多内部发生了什么。
knows a lot about what's going on inside.
好的，关于预测执行，还有其他问题吗？
Okay, other questions about speculative execution?
好的，我暂时把它放在一边，
Okay, I'm gonna put that aside for a moment
讨论一下微架构的另一部分，
and talk about another piece of micro-architecture,
那就是缓存。
that's caches.
每个人都知道有缓存，
And these again, everybody knows caches are there,
但是它们或多或少是透明的。
but you know they're supposed to be more or less more or less transparent.
让我画一张缓存的图，
And let me draw a picture of the caches,
我认为这与缓存结构有关，
I think are relevant to the cache structure,
我认为这与 meltdown 相关。
I think is most relevant to meltdown.
所以首先你有，
So first of all, you have the,
我们有核心，是机器的一部分，
we have the core which is the you know part of the machine,
它解析指令并具有寄存器，
that parses instructions and has registers
并且有加法单元和除法单元，
and has an addition unit and division unit,
不管机器的什么执行部分，
and you know whatever the execution part of the machine,
然后，当它需要进行加载或保存时，
and then, whenever it needs to do a load or store,
它与内存系统交互，
it talks to the memory system,
内存系统具有高速缓存，
and the memory system has a bunch of caches,
在我们所说的机器中，
so in particular in the machines, we're talking about,
有一种缓存叫做 L1 缓存，
there's a data cache called L1 data cache,
可能是 64 千字节的大小或不是很大，
that is maybe you know 64 kilobytes in size or something not very big,
但它的速度非常快，
but it's extremely fast,
如果你需要的数据在 L1 缓存中，
if you, if the data you need is in the L1 cache,
你会在几个周期内得到回复，
that you get back to you in a couple of cycles,
而 L1 缓存的结构，
and the structure of the L1 cache,
它有一些行，
it has a bunch of lines are called lines,
每个可能保存 64 字节的数据，
each of which holds probably 64 bytes of data,
这些行是缓存表的索引，
the lines are indexed the table really the cache,
这些行通过虚拟地址进行索引，
the lines are indexed by virtual address,
如果虚拟地址在缓存中，
if the virtual addresses in the cache,
然后，缓存保存具有该虚拟地址的数据，
then, the cache holds the data with that virtual address
事实证明，
and in addition as it turns out, it's believed,
L1 缓存条目包含权限的复制，
the L1 cache entry contains a copy of the permissions
从对应于这个虚拟地址的页表条目获得的（权限）。
taken from the page table entry that corresponds to this virtual address.
所以，这里有一张表，
So, there's a whole, this is it a table,
当内核使用加载指令时，
when the core is used load instruction,
发生的第一件事是，
the first thing that happens is that,
硬件在 L1 缓存中查找，
the hardware looks in the L1 cache
查看是否存在一个缓存条目，
and see if there's a cache entry
它的虚拟地址与所请求的匹配，
whose virtual address matches the requested,
我们想要加载的地址，
the address we're trying to load from it,
如果这样，我们可以让机器从缓存中返回这些数据，
and if so, that we can just the machine just returns this data from the cache,
完成地非常快，
were done very quickly,
如果它们不在 L1 缓存中，
if they did is not in L1 cache,
那么下一步是，
then the next step is that we,
内存系统的其他部分是用物理地址寻址，
the rest of the memory system is is in is addressed with physical addresses,
所以在这里，我们需要一个物理地址，
so we at this point, we're going to need a physical address,
如果我们没有在 L1 缓存中命中，
if we missed the L1 cache,
这个转换后备缓冲器是页表项的缓存，
this translation look-aside buffer is a cache of page table entries,
它将查找虚拟地址，
it's going to look up the virtual address,
程序在转换后备缓冲器中发出的虚拟地址，
that the program issued in the translation look aside buffer,
它可能不在那里，
it may not be there,
在这种情况下，我们现在有很多工作要做，
in which case, now we got a lot of work to do,
因为我们必须为内存加载相关的页表条目。
because we've got to load the relevant page table entry for memory.
但是我们假设我们命中了转换后备缓冲器，
But let's assume we hittin the translation look-aside buffer,
我们现在可以获得所需的物理地址，
we can now get the needed physical address,
通常会有另一个更大的缓存，
typically there's another cache, another much bigger cache,
这是物理地址的索引。
that's physically indexed index with the physical address.
现在我们有了物理地址，
And so we might, now that we have a physical address,
我们可以查看这个缓存，
we can look at this cache,
如果我们在这里没有命中，
and if we miss there,
那么我们发送物理地址到内存系统，
then we have to send the physical address after the RAM system,
需要很长时间，
takes a long time,
但是当我们最终拿回数据时，
but when we finally get data back,
我们可以填充 L2 缓存，
then we can populate the L2 cache,
并用我们从内存中取回的内容填充 L1 缓存，
and populate the L1 cache with the stuff we got back from RAM
并将数据返回给内核。
and return the the data back to the core.
这就是缓存。
So this is caching.
只是，通过隐藏的 L1 缓存需要几个周期，
Just, by the, by the hidden L1 cache practice a few cycles,
隐藏的 L2 缓存可能需要十几个周期，
hidden the L2 cache probably takes a dozen or two cycles,
而错过那些，可能需要几百个循环，
and miss that, requires you to go around probably takes you a couple hundred cycles,
这些周期，
these cycles are, you know,
比如，在 2GHz 的机器上是半纳秒。
let's say half a nanosecond on a 2 GHz machine.
所以，有高速缓存是非常有利的，
So it's extremely advantageous to have caching you would,
如果没有缓存，
if you didn't have cache
你将损失几百倍的性能，
and you would be sacrificing a factor of a couple of hundred in performance,
这些缓存对于良好的性能是非常关键的。
these are just absolutely critical to decent performance, these caches.
现在，这个缓存是 L1 缓存，
Now, this caches is the L1 cache,
两个缓存都可以包含，
well, both turns out both both these caches can contain,
如果我们在用户空间运行，
if we're running in user space,
这两个缓存，在操作系统中都是 meltdown 针对的，
both these caches in the operating system's meltdown was aimed at,
这两个缓存都可以包含用户数据和内核数据，
both of these caches can contain both user data and kernel data,
L2 缓存可以包含内核数据，
the L2 cache can contain kernel data,
因为它是物理地址的，所以不会有问题。
because it's physically addressed, there's no problem.
L1 缓存要稍微复杂一些，
The L1 cache is a little bit trickier,
它是虚拟地址，
it's virtual addresses,
当我们切换页表时，
when we change page tables,
L1 缓存的内容不再有效，
the contents of the L1 cache are no longer valid,
因为我们切换了页表，
because we change page tables,
这意味着虚拟地址的含义改变了，
that means that the meaning of virtual addresses changed,
所以当切换页表时，你必须刷新 L1 缓存，
so you'd have to flush the L1 cache, when change page tables,
尽管有更复杂的技巧可以让你避免这种情况，
although there's more complex tricks that allow you to avoid that,
但是，在这篇论文的时代的操作系统，
and so but the fact that these operating systems in the days of this paper,
在用户空间和内核空间之间切换时，不会切换页表，
didn't change page tables, when changing between user space and kernel space,
因为两者都是映射的，
because both were mapped,
这意味着，我们不必刷新 L1 缓存中的数据，
meant that, data we didn't have to flush the L1 cache,
这意味着 L1 缓存中同时包含用户数据和内核数据，
and that mean the L1 cache would have both user and kernel data in it,
它使得系统调用变得更快，
and that it made system calls even faster,
如果你调用一个系统调用，
if you call a system call,
系统调用返回，
the system call returns,
缓存中可能仍然有有用的用户数据，
there's still gonna be likely still to be useful user data in the caches,
因为我们没有改变，
because we never changed,
我们没有改变页表或这些地址的含义。
we never changed page tables or changed the meanings of these addresses.
不管怎样，这里可能有内核数据，
Anyway, so there's likely to be kernel data,
即使你正在用户空间运行，
even if you're running a user space,
L1 缓存中也很可能有内核数据，
is likely to be kernel data in the L1 cache,
这些权限是从 TLB 复制出来的，
and it's these permissions which are copied out of the TLB,
从页表条目复制来的，
copied out of page table entries,
告诉机器，即使数据在缓存中，
that tells the machine that oh even though the data is in the cache,
你不能查看它，
you're not allowed to see it,
并引发页面错误。
and raise raise a page fault.
所以现在是提这件事的好时机，
So this is a good time to mention that,
即使微结构优化的目的是它们是完全透明的，
even though the intent of micro-architectural optimizations is they be completely transparent,
那不可能是真的，
that can't possibly be true,
因为这些微架构优化的全部目的
because the whole point of these micro-architectural optimizations
几乎就是为了提高性能，
is almost always to improve performance,
所以，它们至少在性能方面是可见的，
and so they will be guaranteed to be at least visible in terms of performance,
你可以判断你的机器是否有缓存，
as you could tell if your machine has a cache or not,
因为如果它没有缓存，
because if it doesn't have a cache,
它的运行速度会慢几百倍，
it'll run a couple hundred times slower, right,
另外，你还可以判断要获取的数据在哪里，
in addition you can tell where the data you're trying to fetch,
如果你能足够精确地测量时间，
if you're capable of measuring time accurately enough,
你做加载，你就能看出来，
and you do a load, you can tell,
如果加载在几个周期内返回，数据一定已被缓存，
if the load returned in a couple cycles, the data must have been cached,
如果加载在百倍周期之后返回，
if the load returned after a hundred times that,
它们可能是从内存加载的，
they probably had to be loaded from RAM,
所以差异是明显的，
and so the differences are profound,
如果你能测量出几纳秒甚至几十纳秒的时间，
and if you can measure time to you know a few nanoseconds or even tens of nanoseconds,
你可以分辨出不同之处，
you can tell the difference,
所以在性能层面上，
so in the performance level,
微架构绝对不透明的。
is micro-architecture is absolutely not transparent.
我们谈论的所有东西，分支预测，缓存或其他，
And all the things we talk about, branch prediction caches or whatever,
所有这些东西至少在时间上是间接可见的。
all that stuff is at least indirectly visible to timing.
所以，当然很多人，
And so, of course many people,
即使微架构设计在任何细节层面上都是保密的，
even though the micro-architectural design is sort of in any detailed level secret,
对于 Intel 来说，如何实现是他们的私有业务，
to Intel, it's their private business how they implement this,
事实上，它一直以来都是很多人非常感兴趣的，
in fact it's all along been of extremely intense interest to a lot of people,
因为它对性能影响很大。
because it affects performance a lot.
所以，编译器编写者对微体系结构了解很多，
So a compiler writers for example know a lot about micro-architecture,
因为，许多编译器优化
because, the most many many compiler optimizations
都在隐式地利用人们对机器内部的良好猜测。
are implicitly exploiting people's good guesses about what the machines actually doing inside.
并且实际上 CPU 制造商发布了优化指南，
And indeed the CPU manufacturers publish optimization guides,
揭示了一些微架构的技巧，
that reveal some of the micro-architectural tricks,
但它们很少涉及太多细节，
but they rarely go into much detail,
当然没有足够的细节来真正理解为什么 meltdown 会起作用。
certainly not enough detail to really understand exactly why meltdown works.
所以微架构的东西处于
So the micro-architecture stuff is sort of sits somewhere
在透明、可见和隐藏之间，
between supposed to be transparent and visible and hidden and sort of partially,
当然有很多人感兴趣，
you know certainly a lot of people are interested
很多人知道关于它的各种随机的事情。
and a lot of people know all kinds of random things about it.
好的，所以为什么这些缓存的东西对于 meltdown 是感兴趣的，
Okay, so the reason why this cache stuff is interesting for meltdown,
首先，关于缓存，有什么问题吗？
first of all, any questions about about caching?
好的，那么让我来谈谈，
Okay, let me talk them,
关于论文使用缓存的主要方式，
about sort of main way that the paper uses caching,
论文讨论了这种技术，刷新并重新加载。
the paper talks about this technique called flush, flush and reload.
刷新和重新加载的目的是什么，
And, what flush and reload is up to,
它回答的问题是，
is that it's answering the question
是否有一段特定的代码使用了位于特定地址的内存。
did a particular piece of code use the memory at a particular address.
这不是直接的安全漏洞，
And it's not directly a security exploit,
因为它只对你能得到的内存起作用。
because it only works for memory that you can get at.
所以如果你的用户代码，
So if your user code
你有一些内存，那就是你的内存，
and you have some memory, that's your memory
你可以使用它，
and you're allowed to use it,
你可以调用自己的一个函数，
you can and you call one of your own functions
然后你就可以区分，
or then you'll be able to tell,
你可以用刷新和重新加载来区分，
you can use flush and reload to tell,
你刚才执行的函数是否使用了内存，
whether the function your function, you just executed used your memory,
你不能直接使用这个攻击或者它不是攻击，
you can't directly use this attack or it's not an attack,
你可以使用这个技术来确定
you can use this technique to figure out,
其他进程使用的是否是私有内存，
if some other process use that process is private memory,
不过，因为进程有时会共享内存，是的，
although, because processes sometimes share memory, yeah,
你也许还能做到，
you may still be able to do,
正确的说法是，
well, the right way to put it is
你只能找到被允许访问的内存。
you can only find out about memory you're allowed to access.
好的，那么回答这个问题，
Okay, so answering the question,
有没有一个特定的函数使用这个内存。
did did a particular function use this memory.
所以，第一步，我们要刷新，
So, step one, is we're gonna flush,
假设我们对地址 x 感兴趣，
supposing we were interested in address x,
我们要刷新缓存，
we want to flush the cache,
我们希望确保缓存不包含内存位置 x ，
we want to make sure the cache doesn't contain the memory location x,
为了我们的方便，
and it turns out that for our convenience,
Intel 提供了一个名为 clFlash 的指令，
Intel supplies an instruction, called clFlash,
你给它一个地址，
and you give it an address
并且它将删除，
and it will get rid of,
它将确保那个位置不会缓存，
it will ensure that that location is not cached any of the caches,
所以这是非常方便的。
and so that's super convenient.
即使机器没有提供这条指令，
Even if the machine didn't provide this instruction,
有很多方法可以从缓存中清除东西，
that it turns out, there's ways of getting rid of stuff from the cache,
比如，如果你知道缓存中保存 64 千字节，
like for example if you know the cache holds 64 kilobytes,
那么很可能的情况是，
then it's likely to be the case,
如果你加载 64 千字节的随机内存，
that if you load 64 kilobytes of random memory,
只是加载指令，
you know just load instructions that,
这些将被加载到缓存中，
those will be loaded into the cache,
在将 64 千字节的新数据加载到缓存后，
and after you've loaded 64 kilobytes of new data into the cache,
之前放在里面的东西肯定都不见了，
everything that used to be in it must be gone,
因为缓存只能容纳 64 千字节的大小。
because the cache can only hold 64 kilobytes or whatever it may be.
所以即使没有这个指令，
So, even without this [] instruction,
你仍然可以刷新缓存中的所有内容。
you can still flush everything in the cache.
那么第二步是，
Then step two is,
你感兴趣的是某段特定的代码是否使用了数据 x ，
you're interested in whether some particular piece of code uses data x,
你只需要调用那个代码，
you just call that code whatever it is,
它所做的事情，可能使用 x ，也可能不使用，
and it does what it does maybe uses x, maybe doesn't,
现在你想要确认 x 是否在缓存中，
now you wanna tell if x is actually in the cache,
因为是，你刷新缓存，
because if it is if you flushed from the cache,
如果它现在在缓存里，
if it's in the cache now,
一定是 f 导致加载，
it must be that f causes to be loaded,
除非有其他事情发生。
unless something else is going on.
所以你需要加载，
So you need to, you want to do a load,
但是你想知道加载需要多长时间，
but you wanna know how long the load takes,
所以我们说的是纳秒，
so we're only talking about nanoseconds,
比如 5 纳秒对比 100 纳秒，
like five nanoseconds versus hundred nanoseconds here,
我们怎样才能如此精确地测量时间，
how can we measure time that accurately,
这是一项艰巨的任务，
that's a tough assignment,
然而， CPU 再次来到 [ra] ，
however again the CPUs come to [ra],
提供了获取周期粒度时间的指令，
in fact provide instruction which gives you cycle granularity time,
它叫做 rdtsc ，
and it's called rdtsc,
所以我们只需要执行 rdtsc 指令，
so we're just gonna execute the rdtsc instruction,
它告诉我们已经过去的周期数，
which tells us essentially the number of cycles that have elapsed,
从机器启动以来已经过去的机器周期。
since the machine cycles have elapsed since the machine started.
如果它是 2GHz 的机器，
And since it's probably 2 GHz machine,
这意味着，我们这里的精确度是 0.5 纳秒，
that means that the precision we have here is half a nanosecond,
它相当小。
its pretty small.
现在我们要加载，
Now we're gonna load,
比如 junk = *x ，
we're just gonna say junk equals star x,
我们要加载位置 x 的数据，
we're going to load the data of location x,
我再获取一下时间，
I get the time again,
看一下 b 减去 a 的差值，
and look at the difference right, b minus a,
如果 b 减去 a 等于 5 、 6 、 7 或其他，
if b minus a is you know 5 or 6 or 7 or something,
这意味着这个加载命中了缓存，
that means that this load hit in the cache,
这意味着这个函数使用了数据，
and that means that this function used the data,
如果 b 减去 a 是 150 ，
if b minus a is 150,
则意味着 x 不在缓存中，
then that means that x wasn't in the cache,
这可能意味着 f ，
and yeah you know that may probably means that f,
这可能意味着 f 从未使用过 x ，
that may mean that did never used x,
这并不完全是一成不变的，
that's not quite that cut and dry,
因为 f 可能使用了 x ，然后使用了其他东西，
because f might have used x and then use something else,
与缓存中的 x 冲突，
that conflicted with x in the cache
并且使 x 被踢出缓存。
and caused x to be kicked out of the cache again.
但是，对于简单的情况，
But, for simple situations,
b 减去 a 的值非常大，意味着 f 没有使用它，
a very large value of b minus a, means f didn't use it,
在 b 减去 a 的较小值中，表示 f 使用了那个数据。
in a small value of b minus a, means that f did use that data.
所以这还不是攻击，
So this is not an attack yet,
因为我们必须能够访问这个内存，
because again we have to be able to access this memory,
这是我们的内存。
so this is our memory.
关于刷新并重新加载，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about flush plus reload?
好的，我想这是所有的准备工作，
Alright, I think that's all the preliminaries,
让我们回到 meltdown 。
let's go back to meltdown.
所以这是一个更完整的版本，
So this is a more full version,
我在开始时向你们展示的 meltdown 的关键，
I showed you sort of core meltdown at the beginning,
这是一个更完整的 meltdown 。
this is a more complete meltdown.
所以现在我增加了刷新并重新加载的部分。
And so we actually now have I added the flush and reload part.
同样，我们再次声明这个 buf ，
Again, we're going to declare this buffer,
我们的想法是，
and the idea is that,
我们只从内核中取出一位，
depending on we're gonna be just fetching one bit from the kernel,
我们要把这一位乘以 4096 ，
we're going to multiply that one bit by 4096,
所以我们希望使用刷新并重新加载，
so we're hoping to use flush plus reload
来查看 buf 0 在缓存中，
to see that either buf of 0 is in the cache
或 buf 4096 在缓存中，
or buffer of 4096 is in the cache,
之所以会有很大的分离，
and the reason for the large separation there
是因为这个硬件有一个预取器，
is that apparently the pref-, this hardware has a prefetcher in it,
所以，如果你从内存加载一个内容，
so if you load one thing from memory,
它也会从内存加载下一部分内容，
it will load the next couple things up from memory too,
下一部分缓存行，
the next couple of cache lines,
所以我们不能有两个不同的缓存行，
and so we can't have the two different cache lines,
我们在特别近的地方进行刷新和重新加载，
that we're going to apply flush and reload to be to be particularly close,
需要距离足够远，
need to be far enough apart,
即使是硬件预加载也不会造成困惑。
that even prefetch, hardware prefetching won't cause confusion.
所以我们把整个论文分开，
So we put the whole page apart,
现在是刷新部分，
the flash part now,
我们只是调用这个 clflush 指令
we just call this clflush instruction
确保 buf 的相关部分没有被缓存。
to make sure that the relevant parts of our buf are not catched.
现在，我们利用，
Now, we're exploiting,
第 7 行可能不是必要的，
this line 7 is not maybe may or may not be necessary,
但这里发生的事情是，我们正在利用，
but what what's going on here is we're exploiting this sort of,
我将利用这段时间的空隙，
I'm going to be exploiting the gap in time between,
我们做这个第 10 行的加载内核地址，
you know, we we're doing this load line 10 to load a kernel address,
但是它会出错，
so it's gonna fault,
但是我们希望能够预测执行其他指令，
but we're hoping to be able to execute another couple of instructions speculatively,
在这条指令退出之前，
before this instruction is retired,
在它引发故障并取消这些指令之前，
and before it actually raises the fault and cancels these instructions, right,
如果这个负载退出，
if the fault if this load would be retired,
比如在这一点上，
say at this point,
那对我们来说太早了，
that would be too early for us,
因为我们需要预测执行第 13 行，
because it's going to turn out we actually need line 13 to be speculatively executed
才能完成攻击，
in order to complete the attack,
所以，我们希望确保
so we want to make sure that
这个加载不会退出，时间越长越好，
this load isn't retired for as long as possible,
以延迟故障和延迟预测取消。
in order to delay the fault and delay the speculative cancellation.
我们知道指令不会在所有之前的指令都退出之前退出，
Now we know instructions aren't retired until all previous instructions have retired,
这是规则之一。
it's one of the rules.
所以在第 7 行，
So at line 7,
我们将使用一些昂贵的指令，
I'm imagining that we're going to launch some expensive instruction,
这些指令很长一段时间内都不会完成，
that doesn't complete for a long time,
也许它加载其他已知必须来自内存的内容，
maybe it loads something else that's known to have to come from RAM,
所以这需要几百个周期，
so it'll take a few hundred cycles,
或者它做除法或平方根之类的，
or maybe it does a divide or a square root or something,
无论什么需要很长时间的事情，
who knows what something that takes a long time,
它在很长一段时间内都不会退出，
it won't be retired for a long time,
因此导致这个负载在很长一段时间内不会退出，
and therefore will cause this load not to be retired for a long time,
让这些指令有时间预测执行。
giving these instructions time to execute speculatively.
好的，现在我们再次假设，
Right, now we're assuming again,
我们在内核中有一个虚拟地址，
we have a virtual address in the kernel,
执行第 10 行，
gonna execute line 10,
第 10 行不会出现错误，
line ten won't raise a fault, until that,
我们知道它会出现错误，
we know it's going to raise a fault,
但是退出前不会出现错误，
won't raise a fault until retires,
但是我们已经设置好了，
but we're intending, we believe we've set things up,
所以暂时不会退出，因为它还没有退出，
so won't retire for a while, since it hasn't retired,
而且因为在 Intel CPU 上，
and because on Intel CPUs,
即使你不被允许查看，数据也会返回，
the data is returned, even if you weren't allowed to see it,
数据返回用于预测执行，
the data return for speculative execution,
即使你没有权限，
even if you did not permission,
这意味着我们可以预测执行，
that means that we can speculatively execute,
机器将预测执行第 11 行，
the machine will speculatively execute line 11
并获得内核数据的低位，
and get the low bit of kernel data now,
乘以 4096 ，
multiplied by 4096,
第 13 行是另一个加载，
line 13 is itself a load, it's another load,
使用 buf 的地址加上 r2 的内容的地址，
using an address basically the address of buf plus the contents of r2,
我们知道它会被取消，
we know it's going to get cancelled,
因为我们知道这个会产生错误，
because we know this will fault, right,
我们知道对 r3 的写入会被取消，
we know the actual write to r3 will be cancelled,
但是第 13 行将导致来自 buf 的一些数据加载到缓存中，
but line 13 will cause some data from buf to be loaded into the cache,
即使它最终不会影响到寄存器 3 ，
even if it doesn't end up affecting register 3,
所以，第 13 行将导致某些内容被加载到缓存中，
so r3, line 13 is going to cause something to be loaded into the cache,
这取决于低位是否为 0 或 1 ，
and this case depending on whether the low bit is 0 or 1,
第 13 行将导致缓存包含 buf 0 或 buf 4096 ，
line 13 will cause the actual cache to contain either buf 0 or buf 4096,
然后，
then, right, then that,
即使 r2 和 r3 已经取消，
even though r2 and r3 are cancelled,
变化会在缓存中，
the change in the cache,
因为假设它是隐藏的微架构状态，
because it's supposed to be hidden micro-architectural state,
实际上，缓存会被修改。
that will actually be the cache will be changed.
最后，在某个时刻，错误将会发生，
Finally, at some point, the fault will happen,
我们需要在错误后进行恢复，
and we need to sort of recover after the fault,
但这只是一个页面错误，
but it's just a page fault,
你可以或者用户进程可以注册一个页面错误处理程序，
and it turns out you can or user process can register a page fault handler
并在页面错误后重新获得控制权，
and get control back after a page fault,
论文还提到了几种在故障发生后可以继续的方法。
and the paper mentions a couple of other ways of being able to continue after the fault.
现在我们要做的就是找出
And now all we have to do is figure out
加载到缓存中的是 buf 0 还是 buf 4096 ，
whether it was buf 0 or buf 4096, that was loaded into the cache,
现在我们可以做刷新并重新加载的重新加载部分，
and now we can do the reload part of flush and reload,
我们读出准确的时间，
we read the accurate time,
加载 buf 0 ，再读一遍时间，
load buf 0, read the time again,
加载 buf 1 ，再读一次时间，
load buf 1, read the time again,
比较这两个时间上的差异，
and compare the two differences in time,
无论哪一个花费的时间较短，
and whichever one of these took a shorter amount of time,
可能指示内核数据的低位是 0 还是 1 。
is likely to indicate whether the low bit of the kernel data was 0 or 1.
然后我们将其重复几十亿次，
And then we report that repeat that a couple of billion times,
我们可以扫描所有内核内存。
we can scan all of kernel memory.
但是在这个例子中，
But in this example,
如果 b 减去 a 小于 c 减去 b ，
if b minus a smaller than c minus b,
这是否意味着 buf 0 被缓存了。
doesn't that mean that buf of 0 was cached.
让我看看是不是搞错了，
Let's see if I got this wrong,
b 减去 a 意味着 buf 0 是缓存的，
b minus a yeah means the buf 0 was cache,
是的，你说得对。
oh yeah yeah yeah you're right.
现在我们[]，做得好。
Now we're [], good catch.
哦，抱歉，你是否需要，
Oh, sorry, do you need for,
在第 9 行之前是否有一个 if ，
before we had an if before like 9,
我们是否需要 if ，还是仍然会这样。
do we need if now or is it is still at all.
为了帮助我阐明预测执行的正当理由，
The efforts to help me illustrate the legitimate reasons for speculative execution,
即使我们不知道分支是否被选择，也要继续计算，
keep computing even though we don't know whether the branch took or not,
但是这里真正的猜测核心是，
but here the real core of the speculation is that,
我们不知道这个加载载会出现错误，
we don't know if this load will fault, right,
所以机器预测执行通过加载，
and so we're the machines speculatively executing past the load,
理论上，很可能不会出现错误，
on the theory that it's probably most don't fault, right,
即使它们可能需要很长时间，
even though they may take a long time,
比如一次加载可能需要数百个循环，
like a load could take hundreds of cycles,
所以我们希望能够，
and so we'd love to be able to,
这样机器就会预测执行通过加载，
so the machine will speculatively execute pass the load,
即使它不知道会不会出错，
even though it doesn't, not knowing whether it's going to fault or not,
如果加载出现错误，
and if the load did fault,
然后它会取消所有这些预测执行，
it will then undo all this speculative execution,
这里会出现预测执行，
there's a speculative execution comes up,
任何时刻，你有一条长时间运行的指令可能会或不会成功，
any time you have a long running instruction that may or may not succeed,
比如除法，
so like divide,
我们不知道它是否被零除，
so we know whether it's going to be divided by zero or not,
所以除法器后的指令也在猜测。
you know so instructions after divider also speculated.
不管怎样，真正的预测执行从这里开始，
Anyway, the speculation, the real critical speculation starts here,
实际上我们试着，
now, in fact we tried,
为了让攻击更有可能成功，
in order to make the attack likely more successful,
我们确保预测从这里开始，
we sort of ensure that speculation starts here,
所以这才是我们真正关心的预测。
but this is the real speculation we care about.
还有其他问题吗？
Other questions?
对于这个例子我们只读了一位，
For this example we've only read one bit,
是否可以做一些简单的修改，
is is there some likes really small, simple modification,
我们可以读取完整的寄存器大小的位。
that we could make to read like a full register size of bits.
是的，运行 64 次，每个位一次。
Yeah, run this 64 times, one for each bit.
为什么不能一次读取 64 位呢？
Why is it not possible to just read 64 bits at a time?
六十，你需要这个 buf ，
A sixty, sixty, well you need the buf,
这个 buf 的大小必须是，
the size of this buffer has to be
达到 2 的位数次方的 4096 倍，
to the you know two to the number of bits, you're reading times 4096 or something,
所以 64 位太大了，
so 64 bits is too big,
我们没有足够的内存来制作那么大的 buf ，
we don't have enough memory to a make a buffer that big,
我们需要这个设置的方式。
we need this, the way this is set up.
但不管怎样， 64 位太多了，
But anyway, 64 bits too much,
你可以一次读取 8 位，
you could certainly 8 bit of time,
让缓冲器大小为 256 乘以 4096 。
and have this buf size be 256 times 4096.
这篇论文讨论了，
The paper actually argues the,
论文观察到，
the paper observes,
由于大部分时间都在刷新并重新加载，
that since the most of the time is here in the flush reload,
如果你一次读取一个字节，
if you read a byte at a time,
则计算出字节的那些位需要 256 次刷新和重新加载，
then figuring out what the bits of that byte are takes 256 flush and reloads,
每个可能值对应一个。
one for each possible value.
如果一次加载一个位，
If you load a bit at a time,
那么每个位只需要一次刷新和重新加载，
then each bit takes just one flush plus reload,
可以是两个刷新并重新加载，
are sort of two two are two flush plus reloads,
所以如果你一次需要一个位，
so if you need a bit of time,
那么你只需要 16 次刷新并重新加载，
then you end up only doing 16 flush plus reloads,
如果你一次读取一个字节，
if you read a byte at a time,
则需要执行 256 次刷新和重新加载，
you end up doing 256 flush plus reloads,
这篇论文说，
the paper says that,
一次做一位比一次做一个字节要快。
it's faster to do it a bit at a time than a byte at a time.
这看起来有点违反直觉，但似乎是真的。
Which seems a little counterintuitive, seems to be true.
还有其他问题吗？
Other questions?
那么这个用户程序，这个程序要从哪里运行，
So where would this user program, will this program have to be run from,
机器上有没有什么特别的位置，
is there any particular location on the machine,
不一定是，
that doesn't have to be,
我想说你把它写在哪里？
where would you write it I guess?
这个程序是从哪里运行的，可以是一个用户程序吗？
Where would this program be run from, can be a user program?
是的，那取决于你有什么样的权限使用这台机器，
Well yeah, that depends on what kind of access, you have to the machine,
以及你想要窃取的数据在哪里，
and where the data is that you want to steal,
谁知道呢。
and then you know who knows, right.
比如，假设，
But for example is supposing,
你登录到 Athena 机器，
you're logged into Athena [] machine,
这里有另外几百个用户，
it was a couple hundred other users,
你想窃取某人的密码，
and you want to steal somebody's password,
而且你很有耐心，
and you're patient,
你可以使用，让我们假设，
you can use and let's assume,
Athena 在几年前，
that Athena is you know a couple years ago
Athena 运行的 Linux 版本
and Athena was running a version of Linux
将内核映射到每个进程地址空间，
that mapped the kernel into every user's every processes address space,
然后你就可以用 meltdown 得到一个个位，
then you can use meltdown to get out bit by bit,
内核中的所有内容，
everything in the kernel,
包括 IO 缓冲区和网络缓冲区等，
including [] IO buffers and the network buffers and stuff,
如果有人在输入密码，
and if somebody's typing their password,
如果你够幸运或有耐心，
if you're lucky or patient,
有人在输入密码，
and somebody's typing you know password,
你加载所有内核内存，
and you load all of kernel memory,
你将在内核内存中看到那个密码。
you're going to see that password in kernel memory, right.
并且内核可能映射，
And because in fact the kernel probably maps
比如 xv6 映射所有物理内存，
like xv6 maps all of physical memory,
这意味着你可能可以读取所有物理内存，
that means you can probably read all physical memory,
即所有其他进程内存，
that is all of all other processes memory,
在分时机器上使用这项技术。
using this technique on a time sharing machine.
所以，我可以看到每个人的文本编辑器内容或我喜欢的任何内容。
So I can see what's everybody's in text editor contents or whatever I like.
现在你必须，
Now you have to,
这是一种你可以使用它的方式，
that's a way you could use it,
如果你使用的是分时机器，
if you're using a time machine,
对于其他情况，情况会有所不同。
for other situations, you know it would be different.
了解了。
Make sense.
分时技术不再那么普及了，
In time sharing is not that pervasive anymore,
但最致命的场景
but the sort of killer scenario
将是某种云计算，
would be some kind of cloud computing thing,
你使用像亚马逊这样的云提供商，
where you're using a cloud provider like Amazon,
而且在同一台机器上运行多个客户机。
and you know which runs many customers on the same machine.
取决于他们如何设置虚拟机监视器的细节，
And depending on the details of how they set up their virtual machine monitor
或者容器系统之类的。
or container system or whatever it may be.
如果你从亚马逊购买时间，
If you buy time from Amazon,
然后，也许你可以窥探其他客户机软件的内存，
then you may be able to peer into the memory of other customer's software
运行在同一台亚马逊机器上的。
running on the same Amazon machine maybe.
所以我认为这是真的，
So I think that's really,
这可能就是人们实际使用它的方式。
yeah, that's how people actually use this probably.
另一个可能有用的是你的浏览器，
Actually another time that might be useful is your browser,
当你在浏览时，
when you're browsing,
Web 浏览器会在其中运行许多不受信任的代码，
the web browser actually runs a lot of code in it that is not trusted,
是由你随机访问的网站提供的，
that is supplied by the random websites you visit,
也许是以插件的形式，
maybe in the form of plugins,
也许是 Javascript 的形式加载到您的浏览器中，
may be in the form of Javascript, that's loaded in your browser,
由浏览器编译并执行，
and compiled by the browser and execute it,
这是可能的，实施这个攻击，
and it is possible, that this attack could be carried out
通过你浏览网页时，在浏览器中运行的代码。
by code that you run in your browser when you browse the web.
你可能不会，
That you may not,
即使它从网站上运行他们的加载，
even though it's running their load from websites
他们也会窃取你笔记本电脑中的任何东西。
and they would steal whatever stuff is sitting in your laptop.
我不知道这件事的细节是不是真的行得通。
I don't know if the details of that quite work out.
有没有人演示过通过 Javascript 或 WebAssembly 的攻击？
Has anyone demonstrated an attack through either Javascript or like WebAssembly?
我不知道，
I don't know, I don't,
我觉得人们肯定会担心 WebAssembly 。
I I feel certainly people worried about WebAssembly.
我不知道攻击是否真的有可能，
I don't know whether the attack was literally possible,
对于 Javascript ，我知道，
for Javascript I know that,
也许症结在于准确的时间。
maybe the sticking point was the accurate time, I mean.
你不能得到这个纳秒的时间，
You couldn't quite get this nanosecond timing,
所以你现在不能执行刷新并重新加载，
so you couldn't quite execute flush and reload now,
除非一些更聪明的人
whether somebody with a bit more cleverness
可以想出一个办法来做这件事，
could figure out a way to do it,
我不知道 WebAssembly 更接近运行机器代码，
I don't know WebAssembly is much closer to running machine code,
我不知道细节是怎么回事，
and you know I I don't know exactly how the details worked out,
但是，很多人很快就想到了。
but, oh boy was, so many people rapidly thought about.
好的，事实是攻击并不总是有效的，
Okay, it turns out the attack doesn't always work,
原因是，
like and for reasons that,
我不认为，
I don't think,
作者从未解释过或只是猜测过，
the author never explained or only speculated about,
你可以看到，我不知道你是否能看到这个，
and you can see, I don't know if you can see this,
也许你看不到这个，
well, maybe you can't see this,
但如果你翻到他们论文的最后一页，
but if you turn the last page of their paper,
你会看到它实际的输出，
you'll see the output it's actually,
他们在自己的机器上发动了攻击，
you know, they mounted the attack on their own machines
并从自己的机器上的内核中提取了一系列数据。
and extracted a bunch of data from their own, the kernel on their own machine.
如果你仔细看，
And, if you look closer,
你会发现这些很多行，
you'll see there's a huge all these lines
都是 xx xxx ， x 以及点，
are just xx xxx xxx, all these lines x x with dots,
在这些地方，他们没有提取到任何东西，
these are places where they didn't manage to extract anything,
meltdown 失效了，
where meltdown failed,
尽管他们重复了很多次。
even though they repeated it many times.
你可以看出他们一定是，
And you can tell they must have been,
这个论文的攻击版本重试了很多次，
you know they were the papers version of this attack was re-trying many many times,
因为第 6.2 节谈到了性能，
because for example section 6.2 talks about performance,
表示在某些情况下，
says that in some cases,
它们可以提取数据的速率仅为每秒 10 字节，
the rate at which they could extract data was only ten bytes per second,
这意味着他们在那里一次又一次地尝试，
which means they were sitting there trying again and again and again,
在几千次之后，他们终于设法获得了一些数据，
and after thousands of times they finally managed to get some data,
也就是，
that is that,
刷新并重新加载表示两个缓存行有不同的加载时间。
flush plus reload indicated that the two cache lines at different load times.
所以有一些无法解释的事情，
So there's something unexplained going on
关于为什么 meltdown 失败的频率很高，
about why it's quite frequent for meltdown actually fail,
获取一些数据，获取真实的数据，
get some data actually got real data here,
还有一堆他们没有得到的数据，
there's also a bunch of data that they didn't get,
我不知道人们，
and I don't know if people,
据我所知，人们并不确定，
as far as I know, people are not really sure,
它成功或不成功的时候的条件是什么，
what all the conditions are about when it succeeds when it doesn't,
你知道最直接的可能性是，
you know the most straightforward possibility is that,
如果内核数据在 L1 缓存中，则 meltdown 成功，
if the kernel data is in the L1 cache, the meltdown succeeds,
如果内核数据不在 L1 缓存中，则不会成功。
and the kernel data is not in the L1 cache, doesn't succeed.
这很容易让人相信就是正在发生的事情，
That's very easy to believe that that could be what's going on,
因为如果它不在 L1 缓存中，
because if it's not in the L1 cache,
会有一大堆更多的机制参与到预测加载中，
then there's a whole bunch more machinery involved in speculative load
很容易想象 CPU 对于预测加载，
and it's easy to imagine that the CPU for speculative load,
可能还不知道是否需要，
that's maybe not known if it's even needed,
不会费心去从内存加载东西。
would not bother doing all the work required to load stuff from RAM.
但是，事情并没有那么简单，
But, it's not quite that simple,
你可以看出事情没有那么简单，
you can tell it's not quite that simple,
因为论文中说到有时当他们尝试，
because the paper says that sometimes when they tried,
重试了很多次，最后奏效了，
retried many times and it finally worked,
所以有一些更复杂的情况，
so there's some more complex condition,
也许是在 CPU 内部的竞争，
maybe a race effectively race inside the CPU
它偶尔可以工作，
under which it occasionally works,
即使对于不在缓存中的数据。
even for data that's not not in the cache.
论文的结尾也是，
The end of the paper is actually also,
如果你还没读到，它值得一读，
if you didn't get that for worth reading,
因为它解释了一种更真实的世界，
because it does explain a sort of more real world,
我们想找出这件事，
like we wanted to find out this particular thing,
我们知道火狐的密码管理器里有密码，
you know this, we know there's passwords stored in our Firefox's password manager,
我们想把它们弄出来，
we wanted to get them out
然后用 meltdown 偷走他们，
and steal them using meltdown,
你怎么找出地址，
you know what are all the, how do you find out what the addresses,
比如，他们策划了一场完整的攻击，
for example, they sort of lay out a complete attack,
我的意思是，完全由学者进行的攻击不是真正的袭击者，
I mean, a complete attack done by academics not real attackers,
但尽管如此，并填补了许多[务实]的细节。
but nevertheless and filling many of the [pragmatic] details.
我唯一想谈的就是他的修复，
The only thing I want to talk about is his fixes,
你已经了解了一点。
you've already touched on a little bit.
这篇论文发表后，引起了很大的关注。
When this paper came out, it got a lot of attention,
实际上，还有另一篇论文，
and there was actually another second paper
由同样的人撰写的关于不同攻击的论文，
by overlapping set of people about a different attack,
也在 CPU 内部使用了不同类型的预测，称为 spectre 。
that also used different, different kind of speculation inside CPUs, called spectre.
所以，这两份文件同时出来了，
So the pair of papers came out at the same time
非常令人兴奋。
and was very exciting.
所以人们争先恐后地，
And so people hustled,
人们意识到这是极具破坏性的，
people realize that boy, this is extremely damaging,
因为我们现在谈论的是，
because now we're talking about is that
隔离性被打破了。
you know isolation has been broken, right.
所以基本上不用再想它了，
You're gonna hardly, so basically hardly even think about it anymore,
但是这是一种打破页表保护的技术，
but you know this thing, this is a technique for breaking page table protections,
这就是我们如何实施用户和内核之间的隔离，
which is you know how we enforce isolation between user and kernel,
这就是根本性的攻击，
it's like deeply fundamental attack,
或者以任何方式破坏一项极其重要的安全措施，
or anyway undermines an extremely important piece of security,
从一个非常普遍的角度来看，
in a very general way right,
看起来你能看到任何东西。
seems like you could read anything.
所以人们非常争先恐后地部署修复方案，
And so people really really hustled, to a deploy fixes for this,
很多操作系统出了立即修复，
in the immediate fix that a lot of operating systems installed
在这篇论文发表后的几周内，
within weeks of this paper coming out
有时已经安装了这个叫做 KASLR 的东西，
and sometimes had already installed this thing called KASLR,
现在在 Linux 中称为 kpti ，
which is now called kpti in Linux,
这是一个相当直截了当的想法，
and it's a pretty straightforward idea,
这个想法就是不将内核映射放在用户页表中，
the idea is just like not to put the kernel mappings in the user page table,
并且如 xv6 中的那样，
and instead as in xv6,
在系统调用期间切换页表，
switch page tables during system calls,
所以用户空间只有用户映射发起系统调用，
so user space just user mappings make a system call,
有类似 xv6 中的 trampoline 的安排，
there's some kind of trampoline arrangement like in xv6,
你将页表切换到具有内核映射的页表，
and you switch page tables to a page table that has the kernel mappings
为了执行内核。
in order to execute the kernel.
这会导致攻击无法工作，
And that causes attack cannot work,
因为在那里你切换了页表，
because the, in that because you switch page tables,
在 r1 中的这个虚拟地址，
this virtual address in r1,
不仅不再有效，而且不再有意义，
it's not only no longer valid, it's no longer meaningful,
因为没有给它的转换，
because there's no translation for it,
所以 CPU 不知道如何处理它，
so the CPU doesn't know what to do with it,
这个虚拟地址不会被缓存，
like this virtual address won't be cached,
它甚至不在 TLB 中，
it's not even in the TLB,
所以内核没有方法
so there's just no way for the kernel
决定哪个内存对应于这个虚拟地址。
to decide what memory corresponds to this virtual address.
当这种攻击在用户空间中执行时，
You know when this attack is executed in user space,
因为这个内核的虚拟地址不再有任何意义，
because this virtual, this kernel virtual address no longer means anything,
不是非法的，只是没有意义，
it's not, it's not illegal, it's just meaningless,
所以这会导致攻击不起作用。
and so that would cause the attack not to work.
这个 KASLR 修复的缺点是，
The downside of this KASLR fixes,
现在系统调用更昂贵了，因为要切换页表。
that now system calls are more expensive, because switching page tables.
如果你不执行任何操作，
If you don't do anything,
切换页表会导致 TLB 刷新，
switching page tables causes the TLB flushed,
因为现在所有那些虚拟地址和 TLB 都是错误的虚拟地址，
because now all those virtual addresses and TLB are the wrong virtual addresses,
不再与这个页表对应，
that don't correspond to this page table anymore,
它会导致 L1 缓存被刷新，
and it causes the L1 cache to be flushed,
因为它是虚拟地址，
because it's virtually address
所以，在某些机器上，
and so on on some machines,
切换页表会使系统调用变得相当慢。
the switching page tables made system calls considerably slower.
在最近的机器中，有一种叫做 PCID 的技巧，
In an recent machines actually have this trick called PCID,
你可以查到，
which you can look up,
但基本上是，
but basically makes it,
你可以避免切换页表时刷新这些缓存，
so you can avoid flushing these caches on a page table switch,
虽然还需要一些时间。
although it still takes some time.
如果你在网络上随便看看，
And if you poke around the web looking for people,
当时有很多人担心，
there was a lot of worry at the time,
这种拆分，这种两页表的想法会非常慢，
that this split, that this two page table idea would be unacceptably slow,
事实上，这并不是一个严重的问题，
now in fact, that didn't really turn out to be a serious problem,
如果你四处看看，
and if you poke around,
你会发现人们对典型工作量的猜测，
you'll see that people's guesses about typical workloads,
它对典型工作量的整体性能有多大影响，
you know how much it impacts overall performance of typical workloads,
毕竟不会把所有的时间都花在进入和退出内核上，大概是 5% ，
which after all, don't spend all their time entering and exiting kernel, is like 5%,
所以这并不是一个很糟糕的决定。
so it wasn't such a bad deal.
关于 KASLR 修复，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about this KASLR fix?
所以人们很快就接受了这项技术，
So people adopted this pretty rapidly,
事实上，已经有内核采用了它，
in fact there had been kernels that had already adopted it,
因为它防御了一些其他的攻击。
because it defended against some other attacks.
还有一个合理的硬件修复方案，
There's also a reasonable hardware fix,
我相信 Intel 是在最近的处理器中制造的，
that I believe Intel it's actually made in recent processors
而 AMD 已经制造了，
and that AMD had already made,
这是因为权限，
and that's basically to because the, in fact, the permission,
这是缓存的结构，
you know this is the structure of the cache,
当指令从 L1 缓存中加载某些东西时，
when an instruction loads something from the L1 cache,
比如我们试图攻击的内核数据，
like this kernel data, we're trying to attack,
人们相信权限就在缓存条目中，
the permissions or people believe that the permissions are sitting right there in the cache entry,
所以， CPU 在该点检查权限不会有任何问题，
and so there's no trouble with the CPU checking the permissions at that point,
实际上， AMD CPU 和现代的 Intel CPU ，
and indeed, AMD CPUs and perhaps modern Intel CPUs
会很早就进行权限检查，
will actually do the permission check very early
不会返回这个数据，
and won't return this data,
它们甚至不会把它返回给核心，
they won't even return it to the core,
如果权限检查不起作用。
if the permission checks don't workout.
所以这些预测指令不能看到被禁止的数据。
So there's none of this speculative instructions are able to see forbidden data.
我不知道你是否知道这个问题的答案，
So I I don't know if you know the answer to this question
可能只是推测，但并不是有意的，
is probably just speculative, but no [] intended,
但是为什么你认为 Intel 会这么做，
but why, why do you think Intel would do this,
这看起来像是。
like this seems like.
好的。
Okay.
因为在我看来，这似乎是一场讨论，
Because to me, it seems like it was a discussion,
我们应该检查临时指令的权限吗，
shall we check permissions on transient instructions
他们只是想，为什么麻烦只需要一个简单的检查。
and they were just like know why, why bother will need just a simple check.
为什么，
Why bother,
用户无法以任何一种方式查看数据，
indeed stuff transparent and the users not be able to see the data either way,
通过早期检查。
during the check early.
这就像是一条非常关键的路径上的门，
You know that's like some gates on a pretty critical path, right,
L1 数据缓存的核心，
the the you know the core of L1 data cache,
路径对性能极为关键，
path is extremely performance critical,
如果你能减少几个晶体管，
you know if you can shave a few transistors off the,
从关键路径上减少，
you know off the critical path here,
在发出指令和取回数据之间，
between issuing instruction and getting the data back,
这可能会让你拥有稍微快一点的周期时间，
you know that may may allow you to have a slightly faster cycle time
并更快地运行程序。
and run programs faster.
所以一定是这样的，
And so it's got to be the case,
我不知道一定是这样的，
that I don't know got to be the case,
但不难想象，
but it's easy to imagine that,
会花费几个晶体管，
it would have cost them a few transistors
来提前检查权限，
to actually enforce the permissions early,
因为退出后，他们仍然需要所有的东西，
because after all they still need all of the stuff at retirement,
这并不是说早做就能省去他们以后的一些工作，
it's not like doing it early would save them some work later on,
他们仍然必须将错误推迟到退出。
they still have to defer the fault until retirement.
所以所有的东西，还在那里，
So all that stuff, still there,
我只是猜测，这看起来不会有什么好处，
I'm just guessing that it didn't seem like it would have any advantages
而且会有一点额外的工作。
and would have been a little bit of extra work.
以及进入任何一种完全不可见的方式，
And into either way completely invisible,
在架构层面上，理论上也是不可见的。
theoretically invisible too, at the architectural level.
是否有内核决定恢复 KASLR 修复程序，
Did any kernel decide to like revert this KASLR fix,
现在 Intel 已经修复了 CPU ，
now that be like Intel has fixed the CPU,
来再次提高性能。
do improve performance again.
我知道很多内核都是可选的，
I know it's optional on a lot of kernels,
我不太清楚 Intel 的修复是怎么回事，
I'm not totally sure what's going on with the Intel fix,
我肯定他们已经有了解决办法，
I'm fairly sure that they have this fix out there,
但确切地说，我不知道发生了什么。
but exactly you know I I I don't really know what's going on.
我认为在 Linux 内核中，
I think in the Linux kernel,
你可以直接问哪些硬件实现了修复，
you can just ask which hardware fixes have been implemented,
Linux 会修改启用[缓解]，
and Linux you know changes the [mitigation] that enables
根据硬件告诉它的。
depending on what actually the hardware tells it.
也有可能。
So might.
所以你可以这么做，
Oh so, so you can, you can actually do that,
你可以读取足够的关于处理器的信息，
like you can read enough info about the processor
内核知道如何去做。
as the kernel to know whether what to do.
你可以运行你的笔记本电脑，
You can run your run your laptop,
有一个 Linux 命令，
there's a Linux command,
它会告诉你，
that is actually yeah on like which is why it tells you,
在硬件中实施了哪些修复，
exactly what fixes have been implemented where things are mitigated in hardware,
这是范围很广的各自的应用程序攻击。
this is a wide range of these respective applications attacks.
你是说 Linux 会使用组合页表，
Are you saying that Linux will actually use the combined page table,
如果 CPU 。
if the CPU.
好的。
Cool.
我想， 99% 确认，
I think it was, for 99%,
我最近没有检查过，
I haven't checked it recently,
我相信情况仍是如此。
I believe that's still the case.
抱歉，那么人们是怎么做的，
Sorry, so what were people doing,
比如他们是怎么找到这个的，
like like how did they find find this,
他们想要做什么。
what are they trying to do.
他们想做什么，
What are they trying to do,
试图闯入计算机。
trying to break into computers.
谁知道他们实际想做什么，
Well, the, who knows what they're really trying to do,
我的意思是这些论文是由不同的学者撰写的，
I mean the papers are written by various academics,
也许他们的研究发现了安全问题。
maybe you know their research is finding security problems.
我认为更多的是，
I think more that guys find,
人们很长时间以来的动机是，
that one thing the motive for a long time is,
他们想要打破地址空间的随机化。
they wanted to break address space randomization.
他们有更早的论文，
And they had earlier papers,
使用不同的方案试图打破地址随机化，
you know the different schemes trying to break address randomization,
所以，有一组的研究人员
so only one group of one stream of researchers
在这个领域，有这方面的背景。
that were in this area had that as a background.
我认为 project zero 是从一个完全不同的角度来的。
I think project zero people came from a completely different angle.
这是，像 Robert 之前说过的，
This is people have seen Robert said before,
人们在这个领域已经工作了几十年，
people have been working in this area for decades,
试着找出漏洞，他们可以利用并理解。
you know trying find bugs they can exploit and understand.
所以，我想这是一个很难回答的问题，
So, I guess this, how this is a hard question to answer,
但有多大可能会发生另一起类似的 meltdown 事件，
but like how likely is it that there's another like meltdown out there,
因为看起来。
because it seems.
极有可能。
Extremely likely.
好的，
Okay,
从根本上讲，微架构露变化。
like micro, the fundamentally like thing with micro-architecture like exposing changes.
是的，我想事情是这样的，
That's right, I I think what's going on is that,
CPU 厂商几十年来一直是，
the CPU manufacturers have for decades and decades have been,
会加上越来越多的[乐观的]，
you know often adding more and more and more [optimistic],
有许多很酷的小技巧，
there's many many many sort of cool little tricks
在微架构中，让事情进行得更快，
inside the micro-architecture for making things go faster,
人们并不太担心，
and you know now and end people didn't worry that much
或者只是没有引起注意，
or it just wasn't on the radar,
这可能是一个严重的安全问题，
that this could be a serious security problem,
所以现在人们非常意识到，
and so now people now very aware that,
这可能是一个严重的安全问题，
this stuff could be a serious security problem,
但我们现在所处的位置是，
but we're now in a position where we're living
在 CPU 内部 30 年来的聪明想法中。
with you know thirty years of clever ideas inside the CPUs.
所以，很多，
And so, indeed a bunch of,
自从这篇论文发表以来，
since this paper came out,
在这篇论文发表之前，
and indeed before this paper came out,
一大堆，
a bunch of kind of,
这种类型的攻击已经曝光，
a bunch of this style of attacks have come to light exploiting
各种不同的微结构 CPU ，
various different micro-architectural these and CPUs,
所以我认为一段时间，
so I think this is gonna be a while,
在[稳定]之前。
before this all laid to rest.
在过去的两年里，我们看过安全会议，
We've looked at security conferences in the last you know two years,
基本上每年的会议
basically every year every conference basically session
都是关于利用预测执行属性，
on like exploiting speculative execution properties,
看看他们是否会发动攻击。
and see if they can make attacks work.
也许一个更大的问题是，
And maybe a larger question is whether,
情况是不是，
you know whether the situation is,
有 15 、 20 或 30 件事情，
well, you know there's you know 15 or 20 or 30 things,
需要解决，
that sort of have to be worked out,
然后我们完成了，
and then we'll be done,
或者有更高层次的方法出了问题，
or whether there's some much higher levels approach gone wrong,
你知道我们所有，
you know that we all,
这可能太悲观了，
this is probably way too pessimistic,
但人们对隔离作为一种想法很有信心，
but people have a lot of faith in isolation as an idea,
有一件完全合理的事情要做，
that there's a totally reasonable thing to do,
假设隔离起作用，并将设计一些东西，
assume that isolation works and will design stuff,
比如云计算和在浏览器中运行 Javascript ，
like cloud computing and running Javascript in the browser
以及所有这些假设下的东西，
and all this stuff under the assumption,
这可能不是真的，
which is not actually true,
但它被认为是足够接近真实的，
but it was close enough believed to be close enough to true,
这种隔离导致它们不会成为严重的安全问题，
that isolation will just you know cause they're not to be serious security problems,
这实际上可能还是可行的，
and that's actually probably still doable,
但可以肯定的是，这个微架构攻击
but this whole [] of micro-architectural attacks
并没有让这个故事看起来更有说服力。
not made that story seem more convincing, that's for sure.
更进一步的，
Just to add on to that,
我不确定 [] CPU 设计，
I'm not sure a [] levels expertise would like CPU design,
但是，能不能直接扩展 CPU ，在没有微体系结构的情况下，
but to what extent can CPU design be made straightforwardly without a micro-architecture,
仍然保持它的高性能。
while still preserving its high performance.
性能，我是说，人们相信这些东西。
Performance, I mean, people believe this stuff.
安全也不错，不过是的。
Nicely security too, but yeah.
有些事情很明显是可以修复的，
Well, some of this clearly can be fixed,
比如这个 meltdown 事件，
like this meltdown thing,
我的意思是有一个修复，你可以检查权限，
I mean there is a fix this you actually check the permissions,
可能不会损失任何性能，
that probably doesn't sacrifice any performance,
对于已经出现的其他一些攻击，
for some of the other attacks that have come up,
还不清楚你可以在不损失性能的情况下修复它们，
it's not clear that you could fix them without sacrificing performance,
我是说一些非常深的东西，
I mean some of this very very deep,
就像我们分享的事实，
like the fact that we're sharing
这里有很多分享，
you know, this there's a lot of sharing,
比如云环境中的时间共享，
like a time sharing a cloud environment,
有很多共享，
there's just a lot of sharing,
比如，假设你的云服务器上有一个磁盘驱动器或网络，
and so, for example suppose there's a disk drive or a network on your cloud server, right,
你也许能得到云服务器上其他人的信息，
gosh, you might be able to get information about the other people on that cloud server,
只需观察它们的流量，
simply by watching how their traffic
干扰你的磁盘流量、网络流量或内存流量等。
interferes with your traffic disk traffic or network traffic or memory traffic or something.
所以有一种，
So there's some sort of,
我不知道，
I, you know I don't know,
但这是实际的，
but that's practical,
也许很多事情，
maybe it's not although you know for many many things
人们在这些事情中说，
in which people said point that
攻击可能是不实际的，
attack just doesn't seem to be practical,
事实证明它很实用。
you know it turned out to be practical enough.
我认为。
And I think.
所以很多这种微架构的东西，
And so a lot of this micro-architectural stuff,
也许可以在不降低性能的情况下进行清理，
maybe could be cleaned up without performance loss,
或者可能无法在不损失性能的情况下进行清理，
or maybe can't be cleaned up without performance loss,
但我认为，
but I think it's,
我认为这是一个比我们实施修复更严重的问题，
I think it's a much more serious problem than just we're gonna applies fixes,
他们会消失的。
they'll go away.
而最尖锐的地方是密码学，
And the place is the most acute is cryptography,
已经有很多年，
there's been many many years of
人们在研究这种聪明，
people looking into these kind of clever,
通常缓存基于分时的密钥位，
often cache timing based ways of sensing bit set of keys
和其他人的密码，
and other people's cryptographic,
人们在同一台机器上运行密码学加密，
people running running at cryptographic encryption on the same machine as you,
你能猜出我的密钥吗，
can you guess anything about my key
通过观察，通过进行缓存计时，
by watching, by doing cache timing,
答案是绝对的。
answer is absolutely.
而且它不是微架构的 bug ，
And it's not a micro-architectural bugs,
它是经常分享的结果。
it's just a consequence of sharing often.
不管怎么说，我不知道这件事会怎样发展，
Anyway I don't know how this is gonna play out,
这不是直截了当的。
but it's not it's not straightforward.
我好奇的是，
I mean this curious part is,
当人们取得进展的时候，
when people made progress on,
只需测量 CPU 的电磁辐射，
just measuring the like EM radiation from a CPU
并找出正在运行的指令和其中包含的数据，
and figuring out what instructions are run and what data is in it,
使用机器学习有一定的精确度，
with machine learning with like some accuracy,
不是百分之百，不是很近，
you know not a hundred percent, not nearly,
但精确度高得吓人，
but like a scary amount of accuracy,
因为任何超过零的东西都是可怕的。
because anything over zero is scary.
是的，我们知道，
Yeah, we all live in you know that's all,
好的，攻击有界限的，
well, there's a boundary between attacks that are,
在可能的攻击之间有一定的门槛，
there's some threshold between the attacks that are possible,
但是，这看起来太贵了，
but you know gosh just seems like that would be too expensive
或者太痛苦，不管什么复杂的东西都不能实施。
or awkward painful whatever complex to carry out.
而且，攻击真的可能会发生，
And, attacks really could be carried out,
当然我们应该只防御第二类，
of course we only should defend against the second class,
因为第一类通常太贵了，无法防御，
because the first class is often too expensive to defend against,
但随着包含计算机的东西的价值变得越来越大，
but as the value of stuff containing computers gets larger,
攻击者变得更聪明，更接近共享环境，
and attackers get more clever get more closer access to shared environments,
攻击足够可行以防御变化的一种阈值。
kind of threshold by which attacks are feasible enough to defend against changes.
好了，我的课讲完了，
Alright, I'm done with the lecture,
如果有问题的话，我很乐意回答更多的问题。
I'm happy to take more questions, if people have.
谢谢。
Thank you.
谢谢，我有个关于缓存的问题，
Thanks, I actually had a question about the cache,
L1 缓存是每个 CPU 的。
so the L1 cache is its per CPU, right.
是的。
Yes.
而 L2 不是共享的。
And L2 isn't shared.
那么这张图对于每个 CPU 来说是不一样的，
Well, so this picture is different for each CPU,
对于不同型号的 CPU 是不一样的，
for different models of CPU, etc,
今天的习惯是，
the the habit today is
看起来比这个要复杂一点，
looks it's a little bit more complex than this,
通常是多核，
typically a multiple cores,
2 4 8 或 64 等，
2 4 8 or 64 something,
每一个都有一个 L1 缓存，
each one has a L1 cache,
它离 CPU 很近，
that's quite close to the CPU,
但它又快又小，
but it's small fast and small,
每个核心通常还有更大的 L2 缓存，
each core typically also has a bigger L2 cache,
它是专为那个 CPU 设计的。
this you know it's sort of dedicated to that CPU.
然后，通常会有一个共享的 L3 缓存，
And then, and then there's often a shared L3 cache,
通常但不总是，
often but not always,
另一种方法是使 L2 缓存的总和
and another approach is to make the summation of the L2 cache
在某种程度上方便所有 CPU 使用，
is sort of convenient for all the CPUs to use,
这样我可以超高速访问 L2 缓存，
so that I have super high speed access to my L2 cache,
但是我可以得到其他人稍微重一点的[处罚]，
but I can get at other people said a slightly bigger [penalties],
有效缓存大小越大，
the effective cache size larger,
所以，通常可以看到三级缓存，
so often three see either three level caches
或者是一种连接到二级缓存的缓存。
or or a sort of joint to second level caches.
通常 L2 和 L3 是物理寻址的， L1 是虚拟的。
And typically the L2 and L3 are physically addressed, L1 is virtual.
抱歉，有实际地址有什么意义。
Sorry, so what's the point of having physically address, yeah, yeah it's.
是的，这很简单， L1 缓存中的东西是虚拟地址缓存。
Yeah, it's easy, the stuff in L1 cache, a virtual address cache.
如果相同的数据使用不同的虚拟地址，
If the same data is used with different virtual addresses,
虚拟地址缓存不会帮你找到它，
you can't you know the virtual address cache doesn't help you find it,
如果这些 L2 缓存在不同地址下，
if it was cache under a different address where these L2 caches,
则数据是独立的，
the data is independent,
无论你的地址是什么虚拟地址。
is usable no matter what virtual address you address it and.
MMU 在哪里使用，
Where does the MMU use,
它相对于 TLB 中的所有这些缓存。
it relative to all these caches in the TLB.
哦，它不是，它是分布的，
Oh, it's not it's distributed really,
我的意思是，最明显的，
because the I mean the most obvious,
我认为在现实生活中，
I mean I think in real life,
TLB 最关键的是，
the TLB the most critical thing is that TLB,
我认为它通常与 L1 缓存并行索引。
and I believe it's indexed in parallel with the L1 cache typically.
所以如果你命中缓存，
So if you hit in the cache,
L1 缓存，尽管可能会有。
the L1 cache great, although there may be a.
不管怎样，如果你错过了 L1 缓存，
Anyway, and if you miss the L1 cache,
那么现在你有物理的，
then now you have the physical,
你同时在 TLB 中查找，
you were looking up in that TLB at the same time,
现在物理可以寻址了，
now your physical can addressed,
MMU 不只是一个放在某个地方的盒子，
the MMU that was not just a single box that sits somewhere,
它有点[牵涉其中]。
it's actually kind of involved.
好的，但这不是硬件吗，所以。
Okay, but isn't it hardware, so.
哦，一切都是硬件，是的。
Oh, everything is yours hardware, yeah.
但请记住，这些芯片上有数十亿个晶体管，
But remember these you know these chips have billions of transistors on them,
所以，是的，也许是硬件问题，
so yeah, maybe it's hardware,
但我们谈论的是非常复杂的硬件，
but we're talking about massively complex hardware,
它是使用非常复杂的软件设计，
that's designed using very sophisticated software like design techniques,
所以它可以做非常复杂的事情，
so that it can do very very complex and sophisticated things,
所以，它是硬件，
so yeah, it's hardware,
但是，它一点也不简单。
but, yeah, it's not at all at all straightforward.
表映射是否像页表映射一样最终会出现在缓存中，
So do table mapping like page table mappings ever end up in the caches at all,
或者它们总是通过 TLB 路由，
or are they always just routed through that TLB,
因为如果你错过了，
because if you miss it,
TLB 你必须去内存检索。
that TLB you have to go to memory retrieve.
对，所以它们肯定是 L2 缓存可以保存的，
That right, so they're certainly the L2 cache will hold,
从 L2 缓存的角度来看，
from the point of view the L2 cache,
TLB 未命中、 TLB 重新加载只是内存访问，
TLB misses, TLB reloads are just memory accesses,
所以 TLB 需要加载一堆页表垃圾文件，
so that TLB needs to load a bunch of page table junk,
这只是一个内存加载，
it's just a memory load,
可以很容易地将内容缓存到 L2 中。
and it could use, stuff could easily be cached in the L2.
但它必须跳到 L1 ，
But it has to skip to L1,
因为 L1 有虚拟地址，但是。
because L1 has virtual addresses, but.
我不认为 TLB 会查询 L1 。
I don't think that TLB would consult the L1 for its.
好的。
Okay.
因为它是虚拟地址。
Because it's virtual addresses.
然后是一件关于 spectre 攻击的事。
And then one thing about the spectre attack.
你怎么会，
How would you, I,
我至少听说过十几次 meltdown 检查，
so so the thing is like I've heard about meltdown inspector like at least a dozen times,
每次我看的时候都不明白，
and every time I looked it up I would not understand it,
所以这是我第一次真正明白发生了什么，
so this is the first time I actually understand what's going on,
但是对于 spectre ，
but for spectre,
它与 meltdown 有多么相似？
is there, like how similar is it to meltdown?
不是。
It's not.
不是，好的。
It's not, okay.
或者，他们会，
Or, that they will,
我对 spectre 攻击的理解是，通过训练分支预测器，
my understanding the spectre attack is by training the branch predictor,
另一个你想要攻击的代码。
that you know the other code that you're trying to get attack stuff from.
让我们假设另一个进程，你和它共享一些内存。
Let's suppose it's another process you share some memory with it, right.
因为它和你运行一样的程序，
Yeah, because you're it's really the same program as you,
但运行该程序的是其他用户。
but it's some other user running the program, right.
分支预测器使用的表共享在不同的，
You can, the branch, the branch, the tables the branch predictor uses are shared between different,
如果我运行 CPU ，
if I run a CPU [],
可能在同一 CPU 的不同超线程上运行，
that you run or maybe run on different hyper threads of the same CPU,
每个人都看到相同的分支预测器，
everybody sees the same branch sees the same branch predictor,
所以我可以训练分支预测器以某种方式预测分支，
so I can train the branch predictor to predict branches in a certain way,
然后我会让你运行，
and then I'll let you run,
你在运行我训练的分支预测器。
you're running with my branch predictor training, right,
这意味着我可以欺骗你的程序，
and so that means I can essentially trick your program
让它预测执行我选择的指令。
into speculatively executing instructions of my choice.
对，现在只是推测，
Right, now it's only speculative,
所以它们当然会被撤销，
so of course they'll be undone,
但是它们会导致缓存加载，
but they they will cause cache loads,
在某种程度上我可以控制。
that to some extent I can control.
因为我控制着预测执行，
Because I control how you speculatively execute,
如果我们共享内存，
and then if we share memory,
我可以使用刷新并重新加载来检测
I can use flush and reload to sense
你的程序加载了预测执行的哪个缓存行。
what cache lines your program loaded this speculative execution.
哦，那样的话，
Oh, so in that case,
你不需要，
you don't need to, you don't need to,
比如直接寻址一块内存，
like know like directly address address a piece of memory,
你只需要确保程序被预测执行，
you just need to make sure that program will specularly executed,
而在 meltdown 中，我们自己做的，
like in meltdown, we did it ourselves,
但在 spectre 中，直接到那里，
but in spectre just directed there,
这有点酷，
that's kind of cool,
因为你可以，
because you can just say,
只要通过训练分支预测器来加载这个秘密，
oh you know just go and load that secret by training the branch predictor,
而不需要知道秘密在哪里，
without knowing where the secret is,
你知道某些，
like you gotta know someone,
你一定要知道。
yeah you kind of have to know.
你需要知道非常详细的情况。
You need to know great [] and great detail.
是的，抱歉，你得知道。
Yeah sorry, you have to know.
但是你必须自己。
But you have to yourself.
是的。
Yes.
这不是秘密，
That's not secret,
你可能在运行一个程序，
you're probably running a program that,
我知道你在运行什么程序。
I know what program you're running.
好的，理解了，谢谢。
Yeah, okay, that makes sense, thank you.
是的，我只是在想，
Yeah, I was just wondering,
当像这样的一篇研究论文发表的时候，
it seems like when you when a research paper, like this gets released,
给到人们，
it's out there for like people,
Linux 和 Windows 以及 Intel 的人
Linux and Windows and like Intel for them
都在争先恐后地修补这个漏洞，
to try to go and scramble to patch the bug,
但是黑客也可以从这篇论文中学到东西，
but it's also out there for hackers can start to learn from the paper,
哦，这是一种我们可以使用的方法，
like oh this is a method we could use,
我在想，
and I'm I'm wondering,
作为一名研究人员，有没有一种普遍的做法，
like it as a researcher is there a general practice
我们正在写的论文
of like as we're working on the paper
会先给好人，
will sort of tipoff the quote unquote good guys first,
这样他们就可以。
so that they can have.
是的，作者先通知每一个 CPU 制造商和操作系统制造商。
Yeah, authors informed every you know the CPU manufacturers and OS manufacturers
在发表论文之前。
before they publish the paper.
有一个完整的协议，
There's a whole, there's a whole protocol,
这类事情会被接受，
you know these kind of things would even be accepted anymore,
除非你遵守协议。
unless you follow the protocol.
这并不意味着袭击者没有使用它，
That doesn't mean the attackers weren't already using it, right,
因为可能攻击者在 20 年前发现了这个，但是。
because you probably know the attackers discovered this twenty years ago, but.
好的，谢谢。
Great, thank you.
这不是直截了当的，
It's not straightforward,
我认为在这个特殊的情况下，
I think in this particular case,
我想 Intel 不太感兴趣，
I think you know what some Intel was not too excited about,
Linux 社区和 Intel 之间的合作并不完全顺利。
the collaboration between the Linux community and Intel was not completely smooth, I think.
当这种情况发生时，
When this happened,
我认为他们在做一些工作，但是。
I think they worked at some of the case, but.
我觉得有点吓人，
I think it was kind of scary,
因为我在维基百科上看到，
because I I read on Wikipedia,
Ubuntu 补丁是在论文发表后发布的，
that the Ubuntu fix was published after the paper was published,
我觉得很可怕，但是。
which I found scary, but.
非常感谢。
Thank you so much.
谢谢。
Thank you.
谢谢，我们下周见。
Thank you, well see you next week.